<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Æsop in select fables ... with A dialogue between Bow-steeple dragon and the Exchange grashoper.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26536</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17939</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13044041</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13044041</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96878</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26536)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96878)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 404:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Æsop in select fables ... with A dialogue between Bow-steeple dragon and the Exchange grashoper.</title>
                  <author>Aesop.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 13, [5], 14, [4], 14, [4], 14, [6], 18, [4], 14, [2], 11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by most booksellers in London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The six pieces were also published separately in 1698. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) I. At Tunbridge -- II. At Bathe -- III. At Epsom -- IV. At Whitehall -- V. From Tunbridge -- VI. At Amsterdam.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>AESOP In Select FABLES.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VIZ.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>I. At <hi>Tunbridge.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>II. At <hi>Bathe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>III. At <hi>Epſom.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>IV. At <hi>Whitehall.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>V. From <hi>Tunbridge.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>VI. At <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>WITH A DIALOGUE BETWEEN Bow-Steeple DRAGON, And the Exchange GRASHOPER.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed and are to be Sold by moſt Bookſellers in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 1698.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>RIding, of late, to take a little Are, and croſſing by ſome chance the <hi>Tunbridge-Road,</hi> it was my fortune to find a parcel of Papers, which were doubtleſs dropt by ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary Paſſenger, who had made more Haſte than good Speed; and taking them up, I found they were the following <hi>Fables:</hi> which, I imagine, ſome Young Gentleman of Wit and Leiſure, had diverted himſelf in compoſing, whilſt he was obliged to drink the Waters. The Entertainment they gave me and my Friends, made me think of making them Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick; and conſidering the Nature of them, and that they were very fairly Written, it is not at all unlikely that the Author had deſigned them for the Preſs himſelf. There are but two little Reaſons to the contrary, which may be alſo ſoon anſwered; <hi>Firſt,</hi> That they are too ſmall to make a Book; the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,</hi> That ſome of the Fables are too bold, and might expoſe the Author to ſome Danger or Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. As to the firſt Objection, Whoever would be ſure of Pleaſing muſt not be tedious; it happens but to a few great Books to be read through; and many good Authors have defeated their own pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of inſtructing the World, by frightning the Reader with Three or four hundred Pages: But beſides, the Nature of ſuch a Work as this, requires that the Reader be never cloy'd, but always kept in good Humour and good Appetite, which a long
<pb facs="tcp:96878:3"/> work could hardly do; and <hi>10</hi> or <hi>12</hi> Morals are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now to amuſe the Mind, and keep it exerciſed a good while. But, after all, it may be there were many Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles more intended to follow theſe and then I have nothing to ſay, but that theſe were all I found, and thought they were too many to be loſt to the Publick. To the other Objection, the Author having nothing to anſwer; for they are publiſh'd, if not without his <hi>Will,</hi> yet without his <hi>Knowledge.</hi> But ſhould it be granted that one or two Fables are a little too old and angry, yet ſince there is ſome Foundation for ſuch ſort of Mutterings and Complaints from whence can our Rulers learn theſe Truths more inoffencively, than from ſuch little Stories? They will not, perhaps, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſo eaſily to wiſe and good Men as they will to Foxes and Aſſes; and wiſe and good Men will not, it may be, dare to tell thoſe Truths theſe Beaſts deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, which yet our Governours ſhould know.</p>
                  <p>I will not altogether excuſe the Exaggeration of Matters in the Twelfth Fable; for tho' our Bargain be dear enough; yet I can't tell what we ſhould have done without it; and Things, I hope will mend upon our hands, in good time.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96878:3"/>
                  <head>AESOP AT TUNBRIDGE.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. I. <hi>Fair Warning.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>IN <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s new-made World of Wit,</l>
                     <l>Where Beaſts could talk, and read, and writ</l>
                     <l>And ſay and do as he ſaw fit:</l>
                     <l>A certain Fellow thought himſelf abus'd,</l>
                     <l>And repreſented by an <hi>Aſs;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And <hi>Aeſop</hi> to the Judge accus'd</l>
                     <l>That he defamed was.</l>
                     <l>Friend, quoth the Judge, how do you know</l>
                     <l>Whether you are defam'd or no?</l>
                     <l>How can you prove that he muſt mean</l>
                     <l>You, rather than another Man?</l>
                     <l>Sir, quoth the Man, it needs muſt be,</l>
                     <l>All Circumſtances ſo agree,</l>
                     <l>And all the Neighbours ſay 'tis Me.</l>
                     <l>That's ſomewhat, quoth the Judge, indeed,</l>
                     <l>But let this Matter paſs;</l>
                     <l>Since 'twas not <hi>Aeſop,</hi> 'tis agreed,</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Application</hi> made the <hi>Aſs.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="fable">
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96878:4"/>
                     <head>FAB. II. The <hi>Cock</hi> and <hi>Pearl.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Dunghil <hi>Cock</hi> was raking in the Ground,</l>
                     <l>And flirted up a <hi>Pearl;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I would, quoth he, thou hadſt been found</l>
                     <l>By ſome great <hi>Lord</hi> or <hi>Earl.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My ſelf a ſingle Barly-corn</l>
                     <l>Would, ſurely, rather find:</l>
                     <l>We Creatures that are dull, Earth-born,</l>
                     <l>Things only <hi>uſeful</hi> mind.</l>
                     <l>Whilſt they who are divinely Wiſe,</l>
                     <l>And do from <hi>Jove</hi> proceed,</l>
                     <l>Thy lovely orient <hi>Luſtre</hi> prize.</l>
                     <l>And for thy <hi>Beauty</hi> trade.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. III. Of the <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Aſs.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Aſs</hi> were journying on their way;</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Horſe</hi> was only harneſs'd, light, and gay;</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Aſs</hi> was heavy loaden, and lagg'd behind,</l>
                        <l>And thus, at length, beſpake his Friend.</l>
                        <l>Companion, take ſome pity on my State,</l>
                        <l>And caſe me but of half my Weight.</l>
                        <l>Half will to you no burthen be,</l>
                        <l>And yet a mighty help to me.</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Horſe</hi> laugh'd loud, and ſhook his Head,</l>
                        <l>And wantonly curvetting ſaid;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Seignior,</hi> we Horſes never chuſe</l>
                        <l>The Burthens that we can refuſe;</l>
                        <l>And ſhould ſuch Jeſt upon me paſs,</l>
                        <l>Methinks I ſhould be but an <hi>Aſs.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96878:4"/>
                        <l>The <hi>Aſs</hi> quite ſpent, and vext to be deny'd,</l>
                        <l>Sunk down beneath his Weight, and dy'd.</l>
                        <l>The Maſter coming up, took off the Sack,</l>
                        <l>And threw it on the <hi>Horſe</hi>'s Back:</l>
                        <l>And having flaid his <hi>Aſs,</hi> he threw</l>
                        <l>The filthy Hide upon him too.</l>
                        <l>At which the <hi>Horſe,</hi> thus ſadly humbled, cry'd.</l>
                        <l>(Letting ſome Tears for Grief and Anger fall)</l>
                        <l>Whether 'twere Cruelty, or Pride,</l>
                        <l>That I ſo fair Requeſt deny'd.</l>
                        <l>I am juſtly ſerv'd, and made to carry <hi>all.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The</hi> Aſſes <hi>of the</hi> South <hi>and</hi> Eaſt</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Deſire the</hi> Horſes <hi>of the</hi> North <hi>and</hi> Weſt,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That, as to</hi> Parliament <hi>they Trot,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This Fable may not be forgot.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. IV. Of the <hi>Iudgment</hi> of the <hi>Ape.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A <hi>Wolf</hi> complain'd that he had loſt a <hi>Lamb,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſtrait impleads a <hi>Fox</hi> of no good Fame,</l>
                     <l>(Who had a <hi>Lamb</hi>) that he had ſtoln the ſame;</l>
                     <l>An <hi>Ape</hi> was to decide the Cauſe,</l>
                     <l>Having ſome knowledg in the Laws.</l>
                     <l>No Councel was by either fee'd,</l>
                     <l>Each would his Cauſe, in Perſon, plead;</l>
                     <l>And ſo they did, with mighty heat;</l>
                     <l>The Judge himſelf did almoſt ſweat,</l>
                     <l>To hear the force of their Debate.</l>
                     <l>How they accuſe, and how defend,</l>
                     <l>How they reply'd, joyn'd and rejoyn'd.</l>
                     <l>At length in pity to the Court,</l>
                     <l>The Judge was fain to cut them ſhort;</l>
                     <l>And thus determin'd — Sirs, in troth,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Labm</hi> belongs to neither of you both.</l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96878:5"/>
                     <l>You, Mr. <hi>Wolf,</hi> have, doubtleſs, loſt no <hi>Lamb;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, <hi>Renard,</hi> you as ſurely ſtole that ſame;</l>
                     <l>But not from him, if Juſtice might prevail,</l>
                     <l>You ſhould be both condem'd to Fine and Jail.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So two great</hi> Lords <hi>for an Eſtate may fight,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which does to neither appertain, by Right.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. V. Of the <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Man.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Fierce wild <hi>Boar,</hi> of monſtrous ſize and force,</l>
                     <l>Did once, in early days, affront a <hi>Horſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who meditating Vengeance, found his Will</l>
                     <l>To hurt, much greater than his Power and Skill;</l>
                     <l>And therefore, chaf'd and reſolute, he ran</l>
                     <l>To the next Houſe, and thus apply'd to <hi>Man.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I come, Superiour Power, whom <hi>Jove</hi> hath made</l>
                     <l>His Subſtitute on Earth, to ſeek thy Aid,</l>
                     <l>Againſt a ſordid Brute, who injures me,</l>
                     <l>And likewiſe ſpeaks contemptibly of Thee.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Jove,</hi> whom thou nam'ſt (ſaid <hi>Man</hi>) was to thee kind,</l>
                     <l>And ſent thee where thou ſhalt Aſſiſtance find.</l>
                     <l>But this injurious <hi>Boar</hi> will never meet</l>
                     <l>Our Arms upon the Plain, but truſts his Feet.</l>
                     <l>But ſhall his Feet then his Protection be,</l>
                     <l>Since Swiftneſs is the Gift of <hi>Jove</hi> to thee?</l>
                     <l>(Mark it, my Friend, this Inſolence</l>
                     <l>Deprives us or our common Senſe.)</l>
                     <l>This doubtleſs he forgot; ſo will no we.</l>
                     <l>You, for Convenience, will a while ſubmit</l>
                     <l>To be directed with a Bridle and Bit;</l>
                     <l>And take me on your Back, till we ſhall ſee</l>
                     <l>This your outrageous Enemy.</l>
                     <l>Up, ſaid the Horſe then, let us never reſt,</l>
                     <l>Till we have found this curſed Beaſt.</l>
                     <l>Away then to the Woods they flew,</l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96878:5"/>
                     <l>The Horſe his Haunts and Coverts knew,</l>
                     <l>And there his Foe, the dextrous Warriour ſlew.</l>
                     <l>This done, they jocund homewards make,</l>
                     <l>And thus the Horſe the Man beſpake.</l>
                     <l>Now, Sir, accept my Thanks for what is paſt,</l>
                     <l>I to my wonted Fields, and Friends muſt: haſte.</l>
                     <l>Hold, quoth the Man, we part non quite ſo ſoon:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Your</hi> Buſineſs is, but <hi>Mine</hi> is not yet done.</l>
                     <l>Some Service there remains, due to the Aid.</l>
                     <l>I lent you, which muſt be repaid.</l>
                     <l>This ſaid, he light, and ty'd him to a Rack;</l>
                     <l>Where the poor Creature, thus with Sorrow ſpake.</l>
                     <l>Slight was the Injury of the Boar,</l>
                     <l>And might, perhaps, have been no more:</l>
                     <l>But now I'm utterly undone,</l>
                     <l>My Eaſe and Liberty are gone.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sweet is Revenge, juſt in the Taſte,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But ſurely Bitterneſs at laſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let other Creatures warning take,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What Bargains they in Paſſion make.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let Nations alſo take good care,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That they with many Hardſhips bear,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rather than ſeek Redreſs abroad;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which is but adding to their Load.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VI. The <hi>Bargain.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>TWO <hi>Welchmen</hi> Partners in a <hi>Cow</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Reſolv'd to ſell her dear;</l>
                     <l>And laid their Heads together, how</l>
                     <l>To do't at <hi>Ludlow Fair.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>It was a ſultry Summers Day,</l>
                     <l>When out they drove the Beaſt;</l>
                     <l>And having got about half way,</l>
                     <l>They ſat them down to reſt.</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96878:6"/>
                     <l>The Cow, a Creature of no Breeding,</l>
                     <l>(The place with Graſs being ſtor'd)</l>
                     <l>Fed by; and whilſt ſhe was a feeding.</l>
                     <l>Let fall a mighty T—</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Roger,</hi> quoth <hi>Hugh,</hi> I tell thee what,</l>
                     <l>Two Words and I have done;</l>
                     <l>If thou wilt fairly Eat up <hi>that,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Cow is all thy own.</l>
                     <l>'Tis done, quoth <hi>Roger,</hi> 'tis agreed,</l>
                     <l>And to't he went a pace;</l>
                     <l>He ſeem'd ſo eager ſet, 'tis ſaid,</l>
                     <l>That he forgot his Grace.</l>
                     <l>He labour'd with his wooden Spoon,</l>
                     <l>And up he ſtopt the ſtuff;</l>
                     <l>Till, by the time that half was done,</l>
                     <l>He felt he had enough.</l>
                     <l>He felt; but ſcorning to go back.</l>
                     <l>Would look as if he wanted more;</l>
                     <l>And ſeem'd to make a freſh Attack,</l>
                     <l>With as much Vigor as before,</l>
                     <l>But ſtopping ſhort a while, he cry'd,</l>
                     <l>How fares it, Neighbour <hi>Hugh?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I hope, by this, you're ſatisfied,</l>
                     <l>Who's Maſter of the Cow.</l>
                     <l>Ay, ay, quoth <hi>Hugh</hi> (the Devil choak thee.</l>
                     <l>For nothing elſe can do't,)</l>
                     <l>I'm ſatisfied that thou haſt broke me,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs thou wilt give out.</l>
                     <l>Give out? quoth <hi>Roger,</hi> that were fine;</l>
                     <l>Why, what have I been doing?</l>
                     <l>But yet I tell thee, Friend of mine,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall not ſeek thy Ruin.</l>
                     <l>My Heart now turns againſt ſuch Gains;</l>
                     <l>I know th' art piteous Poor.</l>
                     <l>Eat thou the half that ſtill remains,</l>
                     <l>And 'tis as 'twas before.</l>
                     <l>God's Bleſſing on thy Heart, quoth <hi>Hugh?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That Proffer none can gainſay;</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96878:6"/>
                     <l>With that, he readily fell to,</l>
                     <l>And Eat his ſhare o'th' <hi>Tanſie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Well now, quoth <hi>Hodge,</hi> w'are ev'n, no doubt,</l>
                     <l>And neither ſide much Winner.</l>
                     <l>So had we been, quoth <hi>Hugh,</hi> without</l>
                     <l>This damn'd confounded Dinner.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let this, both to our</hi> Wars <hi>and</hi> Peace</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Be honeſtly apply'd;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>France <hi>and th'</hi> Allies <hi>have done no leſs,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That what theſe</hi> Welch-men <hi>did.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VII. The <hi>Frogs Concern.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>TWO fierce young Bulls within th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Marſhes ſtrove,</l>
                     <l>For the Reward of Empire and of Love;</l>
                     <l>Which ſhould the faireſt Heifer gain,</l>
                     <l>And wich ſhould govern all the Plain.</l>
                     <l>This, when a Frog hard by perceiv'd,</l>
                     <l>He ſigh'd, and ſob'd, and ſorely griev'd.</l>
                     <l>He hung his Head, and made great moan,</l>
                     <l>As though he had loſt his Wife or Son.</l>
                     <l>At which a neighbour Frog admir'd,</l>
                     <l>And kindly of the Cauſe enquir'd;</l>
                     <l>Which when he knew, he ſaid in haſte,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Goſſip,</hi> is this all at laſt?</l>
                     <l>If this and that great Loggerheaded Bull</l>
                     <l>Will try the Thickneſs of each others Scull.</l>
                     <l>E'en let them do, as fit they ſee:</l>
                     <l>But what is that to You and Me?</l>
                     <l>If that, replied the other, were all indeed,</l>
                     <l>We ſhould about this Matter be agreed,</l>
                     <l>I ſhould not care a ſingle Groat,</l>
                     <l>To ſee them tare each others Throat;</l>
                     <l>But, Friend, the Creatures of ſuch Might,</l>
                     <l>Can nevet meet in Field to Fight,</l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96878:7"/>
                     <l>But in the Fury of their full Carreer,</l>
                     <l>Both you and I endanger'd are;</l>
                     <l>And all our kindred Tribes below,</l>
                     <l>In hazard of their Lives muſt go.</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Bulls</hi> ruſh on, or when retreat for Breath,</l>
                     <l>They'll tread a hundred of us <hi>little Folks</hi> to death.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If</hi> Kings <hi>would fight themſelves alone,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Their</hi> People <hi>ſtill ſecure,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No mortal Man would part 'em ſure,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But let them e'en fight on.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But when the Suhjects Blood is ſpilt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And their Eſtates are drain'd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To juſtifie a Princes Guilt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or have his Vanity maintan'd;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When they muſt pay for all at laſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That Lust, Ambition, or Revenge lay waſte;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The pooreſt Man alive may fear,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And pray againſt the Miſeries of War.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VIII. Of a <hi>Man</hi> and his <hi>Aſs.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Wretched <hi>Churl</hi> was traveling with his <hi>Aſs,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Beneath two Panniers Load oppreſt;</l>
                     <l>And hearing Noiſe behind, cry'd to the Beaſt,</l>
                     <l>Fly, my Friend <hi>Roger,</hi> fly apace;</l>
                     <l>Elſe I'm undone, and all my Market's naught;</l>
                     <l>And thou thy ſelf will by the Rogues be caught.</l>
                     <l>Caught? quoth the Beaſt, what if I be?</l>
                     <l>What will it ſignify to me?</l>
                     <l>My Panniers are ſo full, they'll hold no more;</l>
                     <l>I carry <hi>Two</hi> and cannot carry <hi>Four.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Twixt Rogues and You, I can no difference make,</l>
                     <l>They are all Rogues to me, who break my Back.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fly, fly from</hi> France, <hi>our Stateſmen cry,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And Slavery's curſed Yoke;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96878:7"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whilſt with out Ancient Liberty,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Our very Backs are broke.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>France <hi>is a Thief; but</hi> France <hi>can do no more,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Than keep the Panniers on me had before.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. IX. Of a <hi>Wolf.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A <hi>Wolf</hi> retiring from <hi>Whitehall,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where he had Stateſman been,</l>
                     <l>Built for himſelf a Box ſo ſmall,</l>
                     <l>That few could be receiv'd within.</l>
                     <l>The Country all admir'd at this,</l>
                     <l>And could not at the Reaſon gueſs,</l>
                     <l>Why one ſo Wealthy and ſo Great,</l>
                     <l>Should cage himſelf at ſuch a rate.</l>
                     <l>Till at the laſt a <hi>Fox</hi> came by,</l>
                     <l>A Courtier alſo, ſleek and ſly.</l>
                     <l>And thus in earneſt and in jeſt,</l>
                     <l>His Reaſon gave amongſt the reſt.</l>
                     <l>Perhaps my Lord Commiſſioner intends.</l>
                     <l>Here to receive only <hi>his honeſt Friends.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB X. The <hi>Plaintiff</hi> and <hi>Defendant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>TWO Travellers an Oyſter found,</l>
                     <l>Dropt from ſome Pannier down;</l>
                     <l>Each ſtoopt, and took it from the Ground,</l>
                     <l>And claim'd it as his own.</l>
                     <l>Since both can't have it all, ſaid one,</l>
                     <l>E'en let it parted be.</l>
                     <l>No, ſays the other, all or none,</l>
                     <l>But all belongs to me.</l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96878:8"/>
                     <l>One Serjeant <hi>Law,</hi> by chance came by,</l>
                     <l>And he muſt end the Strife:</l>
                     <l>Which thing he did immediatly,</l>
                     <l>With his deciding Knife.</l>
                     <l>He took the Fiſh, arid cut it up;</l>
                     <l>(This Cauſe he opened well)</l>
                     <l>And fairly did the Oyſter ſup.</l>
                     <l>And gave to each a Shell.</l>
                     <l>And if hereafter Cauſes riſe,</l>
                     <l>Where People can't agree,</l>
                     <l>I know, quoth he, you'll be ſo wiſe</l>
                     <l>To refer them ſtill to me.</l>
                     <l>My Name is <hi>Law,</hi> my Chambers are</l>
                     <l>At ſome of <hi>the Inns of Court,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Serjeant's,</hi> or <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where all for Help reſort.</l>
                     <l>Sir, quo, the Men, truſt us for that,</l>
                     <l>We ſhall not fail to tell,</l>
                     <l>'Twas <hi>Law</hi> that did the <hi>Oyſter</hi> ear,</l>
                     <l>And left to Us the <hi>Shell.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. XI. Of the <hi>Pigeons.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>THE <hi>Hawks</hi> were once at mortal Jars,</l>
                     <l>Which came at length to Civil Wars.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Pigeons</hi> they ſtood looking on,</l>
                     <l>And, full of Pity, made great moan;</l>
                     <l>To ſee how bloodily they fought,</l>
                     <l>And each the others Ruine ſought.</l>
                     <l>And never would theſe Creatures ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>Till they had mediated a Peace.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Hawks</hi> did eaſily conſent,</l>
                     <l>So Peace was made, and home they went,</l>
                     <l>Where when they came and wanted Prey,</l>
                     <l>And how to paſs their time away;</l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96878:8"/>
                     <l>They fairly made one general Swoop.</l>
                     <l>And eat their Mediator up.</l>
                     <l>Two lucky <hi>Pigeons</hi> were not there,</l>
                     <l>And ſo escap'd the Maſſacre.</l>
                     <l>Of which the One to th' Other ſaid,</l>
                     <l>How came our Kindred all ſo mad?</l>
                     <l>Parting of <hi>Hawks! Hawks</hi> ever ſhould</l>
                     <l>Be gorg'd with one anothers Blood.</l>
                     <l>The Wicked have a natural Rage,</l>
                     <l>(A thirſt of Violence to aſſwage.)</l>
                     <l>Which if not on the <hi>Wicked</hi> ſpent,</l>
                     <l>Will fall upon the <hi>Innocent.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So the poor</hi> Hugonots <hi>of</hi> France.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And</hi> Vaudois <hi>full as poor.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pray'd loudly, in their Innocence,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That God would</hi> Peace <hi>reſtore.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Peace <hi>was reſtor'd; but</hi> Peace <hi>to them</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No Safety did reſtore</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Their</hi> Hawks <hi>employ'd their Power and Time</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Much worſe than e'er before.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And thou,</hi> O Church of England Dove,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Doat not upon thy Peace;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That may, than War, more fatal prove,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Both to thy Wealth and Eaſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. XII. The <hi>Farmer</hi> and the <hi>Hare.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A <hi>Hare</hi> did once into a Garden get</l>
                        <l>Belonging to a Farm;</l>
                        <l>Where ſhe began to throw up Earth, and eat,</l>
                        <l>And do ſome little Harm.</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Farmer</hi> cours'd her round and round,</l>
                        <l>But got her not away;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Puſs</hi> took a liking to the Ground,</l>
                        <l>And there reſolv'd to ſtay.</l>
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96878:9"/>
                        <l>Well, quoth the Fellow, in a Fret,</l>
                        <l>Since you are grown ſo bold,</l>
                        <l>I ſhall ſome more Aſſiſtance get,</l>
                        <l>And drive you from your Hold.</l>
                        <l>And ſtrait he ſends to a young <hi>Squire,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>That he, by break of Day,</l>
                        <l>Would with his Pack of Hounds, repair</l>
                        <l>And ſport himſeif that way.</l>
                        <l>The Squire, as ask'd, attended came,</l>
                        <l>With Folks, and Horſe, and Hounds,</l>
                        <l>And in purſuance of the Game,</l>
                        <l>Rode over all the Grounds.</l>
                        <l>They leapt the Ditches, broke the Hedges down,</l>
                        <l>And made moſt fearful Waſt;</l>
                        <l>They trampl'd all the Garden round,</l>
                        <l>And kill'd poor <hi>Puſs</hi> at laſt.</l>
                        <l>At this the <hi>Farmer</hi> tore his Hair,</l>
                        <l>And ſwore moſt bloodily,</l>
                        <l>Zounds! What confounded work is here?</l>
                        <l>And what a Fool am I?</l>
                        <l>Not fifty <hi>Hares,</hi> in fifty Days,</l>
                        <l>Had ſo much Miſchief done,</l>
                        <l>As this good <hi>Squire</hi> (whom I muſt praiſe</l>
                        <l>And thank) hath wrought in <hi>One.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If our Deliverance from the Frights</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of ſtanding Army near,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And ſilly ſuperſtitious Rites,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Worth</hi> Forty Millions <hi>were;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Then have we wiſely broke our Mounds,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That our Defences were,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Wiſely call'd in our Neighbours Hounds,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And kill'd the deſperate</hi> Hare.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But if, with all this vaſt Expence,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Beſides a Sea of Blood</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Spilt in the Church and States Defence,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Our Matters ſtand much as they ſtood.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96878:9"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Then have we done a World of ill,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>With endleſs Coſt and Pains,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A little hurtful Hare to kill;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And well deſerve the</hi> Brains.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. XIII. <hi>Paetry</hi> its <hi>Cure.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Youth of pregnant Parts and Wit,</l>
                        <l>And thirſty after Fame,</l>
                        <l>Was muſing long which way to get</l>
                        <l>An everlaſting Name.</l>
                        <l>And having heard of <hi>Poetry,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And its Immortal Praiſe;</l>
                        <l>He thought the way to <hi>Fame</hi> muſt lye</l>
                        <l>By courting of the <hi>Bayes.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>He heard how many a noble Town</l>
                        <l>Laid Claim to <hi>Homer's</hi> Birth,</l>
                        <l>To purchaſe from it a Renown,</l>
                        <l>Above the reſt of th' Earth.</l>
                        <l>This kindl'd in his generous Mind</l>
                        <l>A ſtrong and noble Fire:</l>
                        <l>He ſeem'd for nothing elſe deſign'd,</l>
                        <l>Could nothing elſe deſire.</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Father</hi> finding this intent</l>
                        <l>Ill with his ſtate agreed,</l>
                        <l>That, living, wanted <hi>Six per Cent.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Much more than <hi>Fame</hi> when dead:</l>
                        <l>Reſolvd to try to cure his Mind,</l>
                        <l>And change his vain Deſigns,</l>
                        <l>And could no fitter Method find,</l>
                        <l>Than ſending him theſe Lines:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Seven wealthy Towns contend for</hi> HOMER Dead,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Through which the</hi> Living HOMER <hi>begg'd his Bread.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:10"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:10"/>
                  <p>AESOP AT BATHE.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:11"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:11"/>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <p>AND why not <hi>Bathe</hi> as good as Tunbridge? and <hi>Epſom</hi> as either of both? I know the Virtues of none of our Mineral Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, yet find that none of 'em all are ſufficient to purge the Heads of the <hi>Jacobites:</hi> Perhaps you'll ſay, that's no fault of the Water, but of the Head, having no <hi>Brains</hi> to work upon. If this be the caſe, I can't help it; could I furniſh Brains, I ſhould e're now have made a better proviſion for my ſelf. And for the <hi>Jacobites</hi> want of Brains, that's an advantage to the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> conſidering the ill uſe they would put 'em to; furniſhed with that Commodity, they would become as miſchievous as a Monkey in a Glaſs Shop, or a Madman with a Sword in his Hand. Were their wit anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to their malice, what an abominable ſpot of Work would they make? We ſhould have a fine Kettle of Fiſh on't I'll warrant you. 'Tis a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful comfort, good Reader, that <hi>curſt Cows have ſhort Horns,</hi> otherwiſe the Government would be moſt damnably gor'd. But really a <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobite</hi> is a moſt inoffenſive Creature, as harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs as a little. Devil of Two years Old, he'll do you no more hurt than he can; and if he does you any good, he'll be extreamly ſorry for't. He's very well read in the noble Hiſtories, <hi>Pariſmus, Reynard</hi> the <hi>Fox,</hi> and <hi>Tom Thumb;</hi> and this qualification introduces him inio the worſhipful Club at <hi>Epſom</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:96878:12"/> or <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> where they make Plots, and ſuch pretty Plots too as were never known, hanging be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the end of ſome, and nothing the end of of others; but their laſt Plot was the fineſt thing, a very high Kick, Mr. Reader, a Fable Plot, where Birds and Beaſts ſpeak as much Senſe as any <hi>Jacobite</hi> of 'em all; and the end of this Plot was Morals. The <hi>Jacobites</hi> never yet had any Morals in the beginning, middle, nor end of their Lives; and this hap'ning now is very extraordinary; I am afraid they are going to wind up their Bottom, and are in the ſame condition the Devil was in when he turn'd Monk. So much for their <hi>Fables;</hi> now, Reader go on, and thou'lt find that I write <hi>Fables</hi> too, only with this difference, mine are for the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment theirs againſt it; theirs writ by a Club, mine by my ſelf: they have bad ever ſince <hi>Perkins</hi> and <hi>Friend</hi> were hang'd to write theirs, I only one Day. Now whether thou likeſt my <hi>Fables</hi> or no I can't tell, nor do I care; <hi>Fables</hi> I will write for all thee, or any body elſe, and ſo farewel.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96878:12"/>
                  <head>AESOP AT BATHE.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. I. <hi>Fair Warning.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Certain Poet in Lampoon</l>
                     <l>Abus'd the Fop, the Beau, Buffoon,</l>
                     <l>All ſorts of great and little Knaves,</l>
                     <l>Would make Kings Beaſts, and People Slaves.</l>
                     <l>The Court condemn'd his Lines to Fire,</l>
                     <l>And with the Offspring would the Sire.</l>
                     <l>The Poet is in Limbo taken,</l>
                     <l>And hard it is to ſave his Bacon.</l>
                     <l>The Judge doth rail, the Courtiers bawl,</l>
                     <l>And quite alive is grown <hi>Whitehall.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Poet to appeaſe the Storm,</l>
                     <l>Said he, my Lords, I meant no harm;</l>
                     <l>Here's no man nam'd, no ſcandal mag',</l>
                     <l>And all the reſt not worth a Rag.</l>
                     <l>Up ſtood a Lord, look'd mighty big,</l>
                     <l>With Senſe ſcarce half ſo long as Wig:</l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96878:13"/>
                     <l>And by your leave good Maſter Poet,</l>
                     <l>For this wiſe Board's reſolv'd to know it,</l>
                     <l>Who 'tis you mean by Fools and Knaves,</l>
                     <l>And beaſtly Kings and abject Slaves?</l>
                     <l>My Lord, he ſaid none in his Wits.</l>
                     <l>But thinks, I mean, each Knave it hits.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB II. The <hi>Fox</hi> and the <hi>Poultry.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>AN aged <hi>Fox</hi> that ravag'd Woods and Plains,</l>
                        <l>Dread <hi>Foe to Cocks</hi> and <hi>Hens,</hi> and Country Swains;</l>
                        <l>The moſt Tyrannick <hi>Reynard</hi> e're was known,</l>
                        <l>Since Beaſts bore rule, and hector'd on a Throne.</l>
                        <l>He neither young nor old, when hungry ſpar'd;</l>
                        <l>Alike the Lambkins and the Hen-rooſt far'd.</l>
                        <l>But Age retards at laſt his haſty flight,</l>
                        <l>He plunders not ſo much by day, non ravages by night;</l>
                        <l>Grown weak and Feeble, Wit muſt now ſupply</l>
                        <l>His want of Strength —</l>
                        <l>No kind good-natur'd <hi>Fox</hi> will bring him Food,</l>
                        <l>He muſt ſhare the Fortune of the Wood.</l>
                        <l>One day, as hungry <hi>Reynard</hi> ſat alone,</l>
                        <l>His empty Guts and Fortune did bemoan;</l>
                        <l>Said he, I'll try what aged Craft can do.</l>
                        <l>New Methods find, a new Device purſue:</l>
                        <l>Hard by a Tarbox lay, ſome careleſs Swain</l>
                        <l>Had left when he kept Sheep upon the Plain.</l>
                        <l>Projecting <hi>Reynard</hi> with a diligent care</l>
                        <l>Bedawbs his Belly, Sides and Back with Tat</l>
                        <l>Then to a Ditch he goes, where t'other day</l>
                        <l>He did a <hi>Hen</hi> and all her <hi>Chickens</hi> ſlay;</l>
                        <l>Their Feathers ſtill lay ſcatter'd on the Ground,</l>
                        <l>In which the <hi>Fox</hi> did wallow, tumble round.</l>
                        <l>The Feathers ſticking ſtill as he did rowl,</l>
                        <l>Made him reſemble much a larger Fowl.</l>
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96878:13"/>
                        <l>And thus transform'd into a new diſguiſe,</l>
                        <l>Unto a neighbouring <hi>Henroost</hi> ſtrait he hies:</l>
                        <l>And juſt beneath the <hi>Roost</hi> his ſtation took,</l>
                        <l>And looking on the <hi>Perch,</hi> the <hi>Poultry</hi> thus beſpoke.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Kind gentle <hi>Cocks</hi> and <hi>Hens</hi> I am</l>
                        <l>No more your Foe:</l>
                        <l>What once I did, is now my ſhame,</l>
                        <l>And for the future I the ſame</l>
                        <l>No more will do.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I come not as an Enemy</l>
                        <l>Your Lives to take,</l>
                        <l>But would with you'in Friendſhip be,</l>
                        <l>As you may judge if you but ſee</l>
                        <l>The Clothes upon my Back.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Come down, then Friends, a laſting Truce</l>
                        <l>'Twixt you and I;</l>
                        <l>I'll neither <hi>Cocks</hi> nor <hi>Hens</hi> abuſe;</l>
                        <l>Let us ſhake hands as Lovers uſe,</l>
                        <l>Be Friends until we die.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No, quoth the <hi>Cock,</hi> you will as much devour</l>
                        <l>As e're you did, were but it in your power:</l>
                        <l>Your vain pretence of Kindneſs we abhor,</l>
                        <l>And from our <hi>Perch</hi> we will not downward ſtir:</l>
                        <l>You've chang'd you Coat, but have not chang'd your Name;</l>
                        <l>If that were alter'd too, your Nature is the ſame.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In vain do thoſe, who heretofore</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Our Liberties betray'd</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto a wild Deſpetick Pow'r,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And level all our Fences laid:</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In vain they talk of Property,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Or think to be believ'd;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96878:14"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Their Actions give their Tongue the lie:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Who can be thus deceiv'd;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Their vain pretence of publick Good</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Is for ſiniſter Ends;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And who the Dee'l, when underſtood'</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Wou'd be ſuch Villains Friends?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>They'd feed the Flock, only to ſteal the Fleece;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>When the</hi> Fox <hi>preaches, then beware the</hi> Geeſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. III. The <hi>Poor Man</hi> and the <hi>Devil.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>ALab'ring <hi>Swain</hi> had been at work,</l>
                        <l>And all his Limbs had tir'd,</l>
                        <l>By uſing Shovel, and the Fork,</l>
                        <l>To reſt at Night retir'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>So ſweet's the ſleep of Country <hi>Swains,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Such undiſturb'd Repoſe</l>
                        <l>Accompanies their daily pains,</l>
                        <l>That Peace about them flows.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No diſmal Viſions do affright,</l>
                        <l>No Dreams do e're approach;</l>
                        <l>Within the Curtains of the Night</l>
                        <l>They ſleep as ſound as any Roach,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But now the <hi>Swain,</hi> in dead of night.</l>
                        <l>An airy Phantom ſaw;</l>
                        <l>A cloven-footed hideous Spright</l>
                        <l>Him out of Bed did draw:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And led him to an Orchard fair,</l>
                        <l>Where pointing to a Tree,</l>
                        <l>Beneath that Stock, he ſaid, is there</l>
                        <l>A Fund of Gold for thee,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But how, reply'd the fleepy <hi>Swain,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Shall I this Treaſure find,</l>
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96878:14"/>
                        <l>Or know that ſelf-ſame Tree again</l>
                        <l>No mark being left behind?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then quoth the <hi>Dee'l,</hi> ſhit near the place,</l>
                        <l>And thus upon my word,</l>
                        <l>To morrow when thou view'ſt the Graſs,</l>
                        <l>Thou't know it by the T—</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thus did the <hi>Swain;</hi> when he awoke,</l>
                        <l>And rais'd his drouzy Head,</l>
                        <l>He found not as the <hi>Devil</hi> ſpoke,</l>
                        <l>But found a T — in Bed.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thus ſleeping</hi> Jacks <hi>do dream and ſnore,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And pleaſe their fooliſh mind,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In thinking what they were before,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And what henceforth they'l find.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But if they would right meaſures take,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And govern'd be by Wit;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>When once their Reaſon do's awake,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>They'l find their Cauſe beſhit.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. IV. The <hi>Fox</hi> and <hi>Grapes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg n="1">
                        <head>1.</head>
                        <l>A <hi>Fox</hi> eſpy'd a bunch of <hi>Grapes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Moſt beauteous in their Nature;</l>
                        <l>He grinn'd like any Jackanapes,</l>
                        <l>And all his Teeth did water.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <head>2.</head>
                        <l>He ſtriv'd to reach'em, but in vain;</l>
                        <l>He leapt and ſprang as high</l>
                        <l>As any Beaſt of <hi>Reynard</hi>'s ſtrain,</l>
                        <l>But could not reach them nigh.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <head>3.</head>
                        <l>He ſaid, 'tis true, they do look fair,</l>
                        <l>Yet ſowr are, I Know;</l>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96878:15"/>
                        <l>So let'em hang, ev'n as they are,</l>
                        <l>I'll march, and let 'em grow.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thus Rebels do by Governments</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>They cannot undermine;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>They let the King, the God alone,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Tho not adore His Shrine.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Tis well their hands are made ſo ſhort,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That they can reach no higher,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Elſe we ſhou'd all be burned for't,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>They'd ſet the World on fire.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. V. The <hi>Fool</hi>'s Concern.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>TWO <hi>Fools</hi> were born, and might live free.</l>
                        <l>And ſtrugled much for Slavery:</l>
                        <l>One prais'd a Goal 'bove an Eſtate,</l>
                        <l>And ſwore no Windows like a Grate.</l>
                        <l>One lik'd the Faſhions Frenchmen uſe;</l>
                        <l>But above all of Wooden Shoes:</l>
                        <l>Envy'd the Muſick of his Betters,</l>
                        <l>Th' harmonious noiſe of jingling Fetters.</l>
                        <l>Whilſt they at one another grumbl'd,</l>
                        <l>One on a pair of Fetters ſtumbl'd;</l>
                        <l>Near which another pair did ſhine,</l>
                        <l>Tho not ſo big, nor half ſo fine.</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Fools</hi> begin a new Conteſt,</l>
                        <l>Not which of them ſhou'd have the beſt,</l>
                        <l>But which the biggeſt Chain ſhou'd wear.</l>
                        <l>A Country Fellow being near,</l>
                        <l>Said he, the thing is quickly done,</l>
                        <l>Join both the Fetters into one,</l>
                        <l>And let each Man put in a Foot,</l>
                        <l>The Devil tak't if this don't do't.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96878:15"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If</hi> England <hi>ſtill is in extremes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And will not yet be ſav'd,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Call in the French, and late King</hi> James,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And your compleat enſlav'd.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VI. The <hi>Farmer</hi> and the <hi>Badger.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A <hi>Badger</hi> once did ravage all the Fields</l>
                        <l>Belonging to a Farm;</l>
                        <l>Dug up the Earth, and ſpoil'd all that it yields,</l>
                        <l>And did a wond'rous harm.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The <hi>Farmer</hi> halloo'd on his Dog,</l>
                        <l>Thinking thereby to quell her;</l>
                        <l>But being bred to hunt the Hog,</l>
                        <l>He knew not how to kill her.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The <hi>Farmer</hi> ſends for a young Squire</l>
                        <l>To come with all his Hounds;</l>
                        <l>His and their Aid he does require,</l>
                        <l>To beat her from her Mounds.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Squire came with all his Hounds,</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Badger</hi> did purſue;</l>
                        <l>He ravag'd all the <hi>Farmer</hi>'s Grounds,</l>
                        <l>And kill'd the <hi>Badger</hi> too</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Some little miſchief true he did,</l>
                        <l>In beating down the Corn,</l>
                        <l>And breaking Hedges as he rid:</l>
                        <l>So ſmall a loſs was born.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For, ſays the <hi>Farmer,</hi> now my Sheep</l>
                        <l>May more ſecurely graze;</l>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96878:16"/>
                        <l>My Poultry may the Henrooſt keep,</l>
                        <l>I'm better than I was.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If our deliverance from our Foes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And Popiſh Tyranny,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Ben't worth the Money has been roſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>'Tis pity we are free,</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>'Tis certain wiſely we have done,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To keep the Nation ſafe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In giving part as we have done,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To ſave the better half.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VII. The <hi>Cure</hi> of <hi>Malecontents.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Son unto his Father wrote,</l>
                        <l>That he would him adviſe,</l>
                        <l>How men might be to reaſon brought,</l>
                        <l>That never were born wiſe:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>How a tumultuous brood of Fools,</l>
                        <l>that never are content,</l>
                        <l>Might once be poliſh'd into Tools,</l>
                        <l>And fit for Government:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>How thoſe who for many Years</l>
                        <l>Have long'd for Slavery,</l>
                        <l>At once might loſe their Aſſes Ears,</l>
                        <l>And cover to be free.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Father mildly told the Son,</l>
                        <l>In the Attempt he'd falter:</l>
                        <l>No <hi>Cure</hi> upon them could be done,</l>
                        <l>But by a hempen Halter.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="fable">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96878:16"/>
                     <head>FAB. VIII: The <hi>Ravens</hi> and <hi>Crows.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Luſty Horſe, nor long ago,</l>
                        <l>Would ſnuffle, ſnort and kick,</l>
                        <l>Curvet and prance, as others do,</l>
                        <l>Was fallen wondrous ſick.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>'Twas far from any Houſe or Town,</l>
                        <l>No Doctor cou'd be got;</l>
                        <l>So the poor Beaſt muſt die alone,</l>
                        <l>And without burial rot.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He reſtleſs lay upon the Ground,</l>
                        <l>And turn'd from ſide to ſide:</l>
                        <l>His Groans the neighboring Woods reſound,</l>
                        <l>Where Birds of prey reſide.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No ſooner did they hear the noiſe,</l>
                        <l>But from the Woods they flew,</l>
                        <l>Whole Troops of <hi>Ravens,</hi> and the <hi>Crows,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And round the Horſe they drew.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>At length a <hi>Raven</hi> of renown,</l>
                        <l>Strutting like Prince of <hi>Conde;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>As black as any Parſon's Gown</l>
                        <l>He wears upon a Sunday:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Gets on a Mole-hill, look'd around,</l>
                        <l>And thus beſpoke the <hi>Crows;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>We're antient Friends, and without ground</l>
                        <l>We will not now be Foes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>You know, by Contract, we're to have</l>
                        <l>The Carrion of this Place;</l>
                        <l>And you the other ſide did crave,</l>
                        <l>Such our Agreement was,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96878:17"/>
                        <l>No, quoth the <hi>Crows,</hi> this very place,</l>
                        <l>To us is free as Air;</l>
                        <l>And how dare you with ſuch a face,</l>
                        <l>Oppoſe ſuch numbers here?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Ay, quoth the <hi>Raven,</hi> then we'll try</l>
                        <l>To whom it doth belong;</l>
                        <l>But firſt let the poor Creature die,</l>
                        <l>Then ſee who's right or wrong.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Both ſides reſolv'd to fight ſo out,</l>
                        <l>Each do's advantage take;</l>
                        <l>They march, and march and march about,</l>
                        <l>And each one whets his Beak.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>They view the Ground, and mark the Came</l>
                        <l>And the Approaches form;</l>
                        <l>Contrive the eaſieſt methods from;</l>
                        <l>They may the carcaſe ſtorm.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Mean time the Horſe lies dangerouS ill,</l>
                        <l>Yet ſhites, and farts, and groans;</l>
                        <l>Good ſigns, they ſay, in PhyſicK skill,</l>
                        <l>And ſtretching of the Bones.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Horſe (tho helpleſs) by degrees,</l>
                        <l>Began to gather ſtrength;</l>
                        <l>At firſt he riſes on his Knees,</l>
                        <l>And on his Legs at length.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Birds of prey were all ſurpriz'd,</l>
                        <l>And all away they flew;</l>
                        <l>The Battel's thus on both ſides loſt,</l>
                        <l>And all the Carrion too.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thus ſome, whom neither Peace nor Ware</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Can ſatisfy, ſtill hope for Jars;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96878:17"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That by great Princes falling out,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>They may their Buſineſs bring about.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And Wonders muſt be done and ſaid,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>When once the King of</hi> Spain <hi>is dead;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But he, like Horſe, prevents the fight,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And is reſolv'd to live in ſpite.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. III. The <hi>Parſon</hi> and <hi>Whig.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Jolly <hi>Whit</hi> upon the Road,</l>
                     <l>As People ſay, met Man of God;</l>
                     <l>A Firſt-rate Clergyman was he.</l>
                     <l>And of <hi>Bell-ſwagger</hi>'s Family:</l>
                     <l>Ar School the laſh did oft-endure,</l>
                     <l>And was dragg'd uo by Dr. <hi>Cluer.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So bravely mounted was the Parſon,</l>
                     <l>That better Steed no Man laid Arſe on:</l>
                     <l>Stopping the <hi>Whig,</hi> he bid him ſtand,</l>
                     <l>And give the <hi>Church</hi> the better hand:</l>
                     <l>Thou look'ſt like ſome diſſenting Prig.</l>
                     <l>Good morrow, <hi>Parſon,</hi> quoth the <hi>Whig.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Pray, why that, Sir, upon my Coat?</l>
                     <l>Quoth <hi>Whig,</hi> I value not a Groat</l>
                     <l>Thy Coat, nor Church, nor Common-pray'r</l>
                     <l>Nor all Aſh-wedneſday Curſes there:</l>
                     <l>Yet to the Church I can be civil;</l>
                     <l>But ſtop't by Prieſt, it is the Devil.</l>
                     <l>Quoth <hi>Parſon,</hi> if thoul't hold a Parley,</l>
                     <l>At yonder Town's good Juice of Barley</l>
                     <l>Thy looks, I'm ſure, will never fail.</l>
                     <l>For by thy Noſe thou lov'ſt good Ale;</l>
                     <l>And there in a reformed Cup,</l>
                     <l>This Difference we will make up.</l>
                     <l>With all my heart, ſaid <hi>Whig,</hi> I'll do't;</l>
                     <l>And ſo away they both did trot.</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96878:18"/>
                     <l>As <hi>Parſon</hi> near the Road did look,</l>
                     <l>He found a Common-prayer Book.</l>
                     <l>Half cry'd the <hi>Whig;</hi> no, ſaid the <hi>Prieſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This do's belong to me at leaſt:</l>
                     <l>Half, had been thine, had it been <hi>Rivo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But this is mine, <hi>Jure Divino.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The <hi>Whig</hi> inſiſted on his half:</l>
                     <l>The Book was good, and bound in Calf,</l>
                     <l>Wou'd Mony fetch; rather than fail,</l>
                     <l>He'd have it melted down in Ale,</l>
                     <l>Quoth <hi>Prieſt,</hi> that is profanely ſpoke;</l>
                     <l>Nothing's ill ſaid, that's not ill took:</l>
                     <l>I know not, Sir, but it may be</l>
                     <l>'Gainſt Act of Uniformity,</l>
                     <l>Which I remember, do's declare,</l>
                     <l>That we ſhou'd read, not drink the Pray'r.</l>
                     <l>This Book was bought, I muſt confeſs,</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Mammon</hi> of Unrigteouſneſs.</l>
                     <l>And if we ſell it on this ſcore,</l>
                     <l>It is but what it was before.</l>
                     <l>'Twill make us drink, and ſing and roar.</l>
                     <l>No longer now with difference clogg'd,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Whig</hi> together jogg'd:</l>
                     <l>To Ale-houſe come, they both alight,</l>
                     <l>And ere they enter'd went to ſhite;</l>
                     <l>For Guts o'reloaded ſometimes burſt,</l>
                     <l>The way to fill's to empty firſt;</l>
                     <l>They paſt the Glaſs in Bumpers big,</l>
                     <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ere's t'ye <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and bere's tye <hi>Whigh.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Hoſteſs ſcarce could get a ſup,</l>
                     <l>So faſt they drank the Liquor up,</l>
                     <l>She's forc'd to tap another Tub,</l>
                     <l>The Paſſive Ale did often venture,</l>
                     <l>At non-reſiſting Mouth, did enter;</l>
                     <l>So quick it paſt about, that all</l>
                     <l>The ready <hi>Rino</hi>'s drown'd in Ale;</l>
                     <l>No Juice remain'd within the Glaſs,</l>
                     <l>And eke the Pot full empty was.</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96878:18"/>
                     <l>Now good reſerve of Prayer-Book,</l>
                     <l>From underneath the Gown was took:</l>
                     <l>To work again in Liquor ſtout,</l>
                     <l>They Orthodoxly drink about:</l>
                     <l>At every tiff is gulpt at once</l>
                     <l>A learned Collect or Reſponſe.</l>
                     <l>Two Glaſſes in a hand they ſeize on,</l>
                     <l>Which go for firſt and ſecond Leſſon.</l>
                     <l>The Ale doth in right Channel go,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Modo Eccleſiaſtico.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>All's fairly done, without a Trick,</l>
                     <l>No man is here a Schiſmatick.</l>
                     <l>The drinking Orders all obſerve;</l>
                     <l>And not one bit from Canon ſwerve;</l>
                     <l>And drinking Articles would ſign,</l>
                     <l>Tho they were more than Thirty nine.</l>
                     <l>Now, ſaid the Prieſt, the Book is gone,</l>
                     <l>I've a good mind to pawn my Gown.</l>
                     <l>Ay, do, ſaid <hi>Whig,</hi> thy Caſſock too,</l>
                     <l>And Cirſingle; if that won't do,</l>
                     <l>Rather than leave thee in the lurch.</l>
                     <l>I'll help thee pawn the very Church,</l>
                     <l>And ſell the Bells, Communion Plate,</l>
                     <l>There is no Sacrilege in that.</l>
                     <l>Says Hoſteſs now the Tub's on ſtoop;</l>
                     <l>If it will afford another Cup,</l>
                     <l>It ſhall be mine, ſince you this day</l>
                     <l>Have taught me how to brew and pray.</l>
                     <l>Thus two good Friends were forc't to part,</l>
                     <l>Like Thief from <hi>Prieſt</hi> in <hi>Tyburn</hi> Car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>:</l>
                     <l>'Twas want of Liquor, not of Will,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe they had been at it ſtill.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How much Religion is abus'd;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How little Honeſty is us'd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By thoſe who do profeſs the ſame;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How much the Sacred Name</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Is every where profan'd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How deeply ſtain'd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96878:19"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Parſon<hi>'s Gown,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Friend to none,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But to himſelf alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lord I how we heard'em cant, and pray, and whine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And preach up Monarchy of Right Divine.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Why did they ſo?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It was their Intereſt ſo to do.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When Right divine new Clergy-Men did ſeek,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Seiz'd on the Church, and made the Tithe-pig ſqueek;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Paſſive Obedience now was preacht no more;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Inſtead of which the Churches Canons roar,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Reach'd with Complaints the Belgick Shoar,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Norther Lion o're the Seas did paſs,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſcar'd away the Church's Aſs;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Church, by whoſe advice he ruin'd was.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They'll make, and govern Kings, but none obey,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But where their Intereſt leads the way</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Intereſt, for which they'd pawn their very God,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Their Church, their Principles: 'tis very odd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A King ſhou'd truſt men will be brib'd with Gold,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And not be heedful when another's ſold.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:19"/>
                  <p>AESOP AT EPSOM.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:20"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:20"/>
                  <head>To his Excellency <hi>Charles Montague,</hi> Eſq; one of the Lord's Juſtices for the Adminiſtration of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Affaires during the <hi>King's</hi> Abſence, firſt Lord Commiſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Treaſury, Chancellor of the Exchequer, and one of His Majeſty's moſt Honourable Privy Council.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THo' a Preſent of <hi>Fables</hi> to Your Excellency the immitable Author of the <hi>Country-Mouſe,</hi> and <hi>City-Mouſe,</hi> may at this time ſeem improper: Yet a Preſent of <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the ſame Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which You have been ſo ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſucceſsful in the Preſervation of, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but carry its Acceptance with it. That Liberty which Your <hi>Excellency</hi> gave the World ſo ſweet a taſte of in Your moſt incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable <hi>Fable,</hi> and which afterwards You was ſo inſtrumental in continuing to us, is
<pb facs="tcp:96878:21"/> in part the Subject of <hi>theſe.</hi> And as <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop at Tunbridge,</hi> by <hi>feign'd</hi> and <hi>ſurrepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> Fables, ſeems to bewail the change of the late Government, ſo <hi>Aeſop at Epſom</hi> with <hi>real</hi> and <hi>genuine</hi> reſoyceth at the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabliſhment of this. Sir, Your Execellency's great Example has ſuch a prevailing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, as to make the meaneſt Subject ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous for the Publick Good, and to ſee that <hi>Revolution</hi> become the ſubject of <hi>Satyr,</hi> which has giv'n ſuch opportunities for <hi>Hene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyrick,</hi> (and whoſe <hi>Royal Author</hi> has had ſuch immortal Commendations from Your <hi>Excellency's</hi> the beſt of Pens) could not but add very much to my Reſentments in the following Papers. But, Sir, to give no further interruption to a Gentleman whoſe very <hi>Leiſure</hi> is employ'd for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Safety, I ſhall not encroach upon Your time any further than to beg Your Acceptance of this <hi>poor Entertainment,</hi> which, ſhall make me add to my Endeavours of appoving my ſelf in a more ſubſtantial way,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     <signed>Your Excellency's moſt Obedient Servant.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96878:21"/>
                  <head>AESOP AT EPSOM.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. I. Of the <hi>Fox</hi> and the <hi>Stork.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Subtil Fox, well practis'd in deſign,</l>
                     <l>Invites a Stork, that He with him will dine</l>
                     <l>A match, ſays Stork, Sir Reynard it's agreed,</l>
                     <l>And home he goes, and much reſolv'd to feed.</l>
                     <l>Nothing will ſerve, but that <hi>He's ſure the Beaſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Will ſoon repent He'd brought him for a Gueſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His Stomach was ſo empty, and ſo great,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Zounds! He himſelf ſhould finiſh all the treat.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Fox ſmiles, and in his <hi>Cubs</hi> the Dinner bring,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Soop,</hi> and <hi>Pottage,</hi> a Banquet for a King.</l>
                     <l>Fall on, my gueſt, ſaid Fox, and down he pour's</l>
                     <l>The liquid Feaſt which He himſelf devours.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dear Stork,</hi> He crys, <hi>'Slife. Child, why doſt not Peck,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Stork he ſtretches, and extends his neck.</l>
                     <l>But nothing can get up within his Bill,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt Reynard licks it up, and Eats his fill;</l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96878:22"/>
                     <l>At length perceiving how he had been ſerv'd,</l>
                     <l>He homeward Stalks, or he muſt elſe have Strav'd,</l>
                     <l>But Mindfull of the Fox his empty Treat,</l>
                     <l>Sends to Invite Him to a diſh of Meat.</l>
                     <l>The Fox not thinking Storks had had the ſenſe</l>
                     <l>To mind affronts, or take the leaſt offence.</l>
                     <l>Took him at's word, and ſaid, Sir Stork content,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I'll ſee what Houſe you keep,</hi> and Home wi'him <hi>went.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Table Spread, and every thing compleat,</l>
                     <l>That might put Fox in mind He was to eat:</l>
                     <l>Two Servant Storks upon the Table plac'd</l>
                     <l>A Narrow long-neck'd Glaſs which held the Feaſt;</l>
                     <l>Lampreys and Eels within it might be ſeen,</l>
                     <l>The Glaſs was ſo tranſparant and ſo clean,</l>
                     <l>When Stork, <hi>Sans ceremony, Sir, begin,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You ſee your Entertainment here, within,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I'll ſhew the way;</hi> and in his Beak he thruſt</l>
                     <l>Whil'ſt Reynard try'd in vain, add trying curs'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lord,</hi> ſaid the Stork, <hi>are you a Beaſt of thought,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And yet no Broth, or Soop, or Pottage brought?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I'd e'en fetch ſome, and fill the Veſſel up,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You then, although You could not eat, might ſup.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL</head>
                        <l>The Application ſoon is made</l>
                        <l>By any that's a Reader,</l>
                        <l>One in his turn the Fool has play'd,</l>
                        <l>And whoſe turn's now conſider:</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Tunbridge Aeſop</hi> firſt has given</l>
                        <l>The Town a Diſh of Meat,</l>
                        <l>And faith, to make the Tallies ever,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Epſom</hi> ſhould alſo treat.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="fable">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96878:22"/>
                     <head>FAB. II. Of the <hi>Lamb</hi> and the <hi>Wolf.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Wolf as he look'd our for prey,</l>
                     <l>And went in ſearch of food,</l>
                     <l>Perceiv'd a Lamb and Goat in's way</l>
                     <l>Come jogging on the Road.</l>
                     <l>Mutton he lov'd, but did not dare</l>
                     <l>Faſten on that he ſpy'd,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt <hi>Hircus</hi> with his Horns was there,</l>
                     <l>And thus to part them try'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Home from this Beaſt for ſhame, Sir Lamb.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It grieves my very Soul,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To ſee you leave a Noble Dam,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And walk with Goat ſo foul.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Goat! fy on't, the very worſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of all the Brutal Race;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A ſtinking Animal and curs'd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Woods, and Fields diſgrace.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hark you,</hi> ſaid Lamb; <hi>I plainly know</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whom you your Tricks would put on,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And what you mean by gaping ſo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Poor Wolf! he wants ſome Mutton.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I'thank you for th' Advice you lend,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And wonder not you ſhou'd</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Like me much better than my Friend,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Since I am much better Food.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>So when the Wars broke out at firſt,</l>
                        <l>And <hi>France</hi> prepar'd for fighting,</l>
                        <l>Lord! how her Mighty Monarch curs'd</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Dutch</hi> and us uniting!</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Per Dieu, ſaid he, the Britiſh Race</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of Heroes once the Chief</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Joyn with a Land ſo curſed Baſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And ask of them relief!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96878:23"/>
                        <l>But had his Aim ſuccceſsful been</l>
                        <l>And us from them remov'd,</l>
                        <l>We then the ſad Effects had ſeen.</l>
                        <l>And Fables moral prov'd.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. III. Of the <hi>Sun</hi> and the <hi>North-wind.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>BEtwixt the Sun and Wind, aroſe</l>
                        <l>A Quarrer, like to end in Blows,</l>
                        <l>If both of 'em had not rather choſe</l>
                        <l>A fitting Mediator.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>It ſeems that this Contention grew</l>
                        <l>From which was Strongeſt of Two.</l>
                        <l>And down their Wagers ſtrait they threw</l>
                        <l>Thus to decide the matter.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By chance a Traveller came by,</l>
                        <l>And both with one united cry,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>On him let us our Forces try</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To finish the Diſpute:</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He that the firſt a Way could find</l>
                        <l>To make him leave his Cloak behind</l>
                        <l>Should win; <hi>it's dine, agreed, ſaid Wind.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Said Sun, <hi>content, I'll do't.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>When Boreas ſummon'd every Blaſt,</l>
                        <l>And at him all his fury caſt,</l>
                        <l>But flinging round his Cloak, he paſs'd</l>
                        <l>And forwarded his Journey:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Sol ſmiles, and gath'ring all his Rays,</l>
                        <l>Sure of the Conqueſt and the Bays,</l>
                        <l>I'll make you quit your Cloack, he ſays,</l>
                        <l>Or elſe, by God, I'll burn ye.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Straight Paſſenger began to ſwear,</l>
                        <l>Enrag'd and troubled with the Heat,</l>
                        <l>And in a moſt confounded Pett,</l>
                        <l>At laſt flung off the Garment</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96878:23"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Boreas,</hi> ſaid Sol, <hi>See yonder Cloak,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Wagers won and thou art broke,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And up in haſte the Stakes he took,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And that was all the harm in't.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>Thus bluſt'ring Kings like Boreas often fail;</l>
                        <l>Whilſt others like the Conqu'ring Sun prevail;</l>
                        <l>Numbers may fright and diſmal Fancies raiſe,</l>
                        <l>But what can Numbers in improper Ways?</l>
                        <l>Whilſt at Campeign extended Armies ſhine,</l>
                        <l>And <hi>France</hi> her infant Printes fight, and dine;</l>
                        <l>Whilſt <hi>Boufflers</hi> treats the Ladies with a Song,</l>
                        <l>And Duke <hi>de Berry</hi> learns the Spaniſh Tongue,</l>
                        <l>A Prince at Cell, who Seemingly appears</l>
                        <l>Thoughtleſs of Arms ſince now releas'd from <hi>Wars:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Amid'ſt his Sports, ſhall-fit Expedients find</l>
                        <l>To cheat the dangers by their Arms deſign'd:</l>
                        <l>And one poor Hunting Matcl. perhaps may break:</l>
                        <l>The Meaſures which their fam'd Encampments take.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. IV. Of the <hi>Trumpeter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Trumpeter in time of War</l>
                     <l>Was in the Battle taken;</l>
                     <l>And Dead almoſt with very fear.</l>
                     <l>Try'd thus to ſave his Bacon.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dear Sirs, if guiltleſs Actions ſave,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or Innocence ſecures,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>From you the grant of Life I crave,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Who ne'er, endanger'd yours.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nor Sword, nor Muſquet have I born,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or any other Weapon worn</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Than what is in my hand:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This Trumpet never gave a wound,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96878:24"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or utter'd any thing but empty ſound,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And that too by command.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Off with the Dog, and fetch the Rope,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Said Enemy, <hi>and tye him up,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Villain! never ſpare him.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Zounds! That ſame Inſtrument is worſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Than Sword, and Gun, and every Curſe;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And we've moſt cauſe to fear him,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Since from his blaſts, thoſe wounds at firſt proceed,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By which ſo many Thouſands of us bleed.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>So crys an Author who has ſpent his ſpleen,</l>
                        <l>What harm can ſilly <hi>Fables</hi> mean?</l>
                        <l>Or how can <hi>Faction</hi> takes its birth,</l>
                        <l>From a few Tales, and unprovoking Mirth?</l>
                        <l>They may perhaps delight,</l>
                        <l>But reſt aſſur'd they'll never Fight,</l>
                        <l>The Beaſt I-treat of cannot Plot</l>
                        <l>Or traffick in Sedition: what of that?</l>
                        <l>When if he rail'd like <hi>O—ts,</hi> like <hi>S—</hi> Fought,</l>
                        <l>Curſ'd like a Man at <hi>Sam's,</hi> like <hi>M—</hi> thought,</l>
                        <l>All join'd together ne'er was able</l>
                        <l>To ſhow the malice of one ſingle Fable.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. V. Of the <hi>Apple</hi> and the <hi>Horſe-Turd.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>AN Apple falling from a Tree</l>
                     <l>Which near a River ſtood,</l>
                     <l>With Horſe Turd in his Company</l>
                     <l>Was ſailing down the Flood.</l>
                     <l>When Turd ambitious to diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>A thing ſo much above it,</l>
                     <l>Would into Converſation force</l>
                     <l>As down the River drove it,</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96878:24"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lord! Madam, what a pleaſant Stream</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Is this in which we ride?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Siſter! How we Two Apples ſwim?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The foul <hi>Sir-rev'rence</hi> cry'd.</l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>A Thread-bare Wriner who perchance</l>
                        <l>Has not one Farthing paid,</l>
                        <l>To carry on the War with <hi>France,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Towards the Royal Aid.</l>
                        <l>Crys, Damn this curs'd confounded Peace,</l>
                        <l>It Forty Millions coſt,</l>
                        <l>And <hi>we</hi> could not procure <hi>our</hi> Eaſe</l>
                        <l>Till All <hi>our</hi> Wealth was loſt.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VI. of the <hi>Covetous</hi> and the <hi>Envious Man.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>TWO men to <hi>Jove</hi> their Prayers made</l>
                     <l>For ſome kind Earthly Bleſſing,</l>
                     <l>One never ſatisfy'd with what he had,</l>
                     <l>Tho' rich beyond Expreſſing.</l>
                     <l>Th' other was envious, nor car'd</l>
                     <l>What miſchief e're befell Him,</l>
                     <l>So that his Comrade was not ſpar'd,</l>
                     <l>And what ſhould kill him, kill him:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Jove</hi> Teaz'd with their Petitions, ſent</l>
                     <l>His Son <hi>Appolo</hi> to 'em,</l>
                     <l>To try to give'em both content,</l>
                     <l>And know what ſervice. He could do'em.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ask,</hi> ſaid <hi>Appollo, Friends what 'ere</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You want th'out further trouble,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And what is ask'd from either pray'r</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>T'other ſhall have it double.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With that, the parſimonious Cuff</l>
                     <l>For Wealth did loudly call,</l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96878:25"/>
                     <l>Which downward fell but ne'r enough</l>
                     <l>For his deſires could fall.</l>
                     <l>Still as he ask'd, the Richeſs came,</l>
                     <l>And doubled on the other,</l>
                     <l>Tho' ſtill his prayer was the ſame</l>
                     <l>Which ſtill enrich'd his Brother,</l>
                     <l>Next in his turn, Sir Envy kneel'd.</l>
                     <l>And with a bale-ful Eye,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dear</hi> Phaebus <hi>to my prayer yield</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And barken to my cry,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Now oh! juſt now thou Pow'r divine</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This favour let me find,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Put out this ſingle Eye of mine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That his may both be blind.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VII. Of the <hi>Beaver,</hi> and the <hi>Hunters.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Beaver being cloſe purſu'd</l>
                     <l>By Hunters, Horſe, and Hounds;</l>
                     <l>And neither ſafe, within the Wood,</l>
                     <l>Nor in the open Grounds,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I know full well (and ſtep'd aſide)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The reaſons why I'm chas'd, he cry'd.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And much lament the, Cauſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Stones are what they want, and I</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Muſt either part with them, or die,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And glut the Beagles jaws:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With that, though he was loath to part</l>
                     <l>With things as precious as his heart,</l>
                     <l>Or with a quiet mind</l>
                     <l>Surrender up the pride of all his kind,</l>
                     <l>Yet life was ſweet, and utt'ring forth ſome groans,</l>
                     <l>Off went his dear beloved Stones,</l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96878:25"/>
                     <l>Which in the Hunters way</l>
                     <l>The Melancholy Beaſt did lay.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Call in the Hounds, the fierce Purſuers ſaid,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>We've caught the Game, and have our Markets made;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And taking up the Prize they went</l>
                     <l>All homeward with content.</l>
                     <l>Whliſt the Enervate Beaſt return'd,</l>
                     <l>To graze in quiet on the plain:</l>
                     <l>And never after this Misfortune mourn'd,</l>
                     <l>Or fled from <hi>Hunters</hi> or from <hi>Hounds</hi> again.</l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>If a certain great Prince had but done as this Beaſt,</l>
                        <l>And inſtead of each Stone gotten rid of each Prieſt,</l>
                        <l>He had ſtill been King, whom his People had bleſs'd.</l>
                        <l>But ſince He bad rather keep in with <hi>Ned Petre</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And likes Fryers, and Monks for his company fitter:</l>
                        <l>Let him <hi>now</hi> keep his <hi>Stones,</hi> for there's none but has <hi>bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VIII. The <hi>Lion</hi> and the <hi>Fox.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Fox, a Lion's Chaplain, when</l>
                     <l>The Beaſts began to cry,</l>
                     <l>And gather round their Monarch's Den</l>
                     <l>For Antient <hi>Liberty;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Said, <hi>may it pleaſe my Sov'raign, Lord,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Your ſubjects are your Slaves,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And if they dare to ſpeak a word,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Your Throat may be their Graves.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With that the Monarch Wiſely ſmil'd</l>
                     <l>At good Sir Crapes advice,</l>
                     <l>And ſaid, <hi>go fetch your youngeſt Child,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Stomach's ſomething nice.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sir,</hi> ſaid the Fox, <hi>Your in the wrong,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I muſt your pardon crave,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96878:26"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Parſons alone to Jove belong,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And no Controulers have.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>So in late times the Pulpits rung,</l>
                        <l>With Paſſive <hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And all the burthen of their Song</l>
                        <l>Was <hi>Duty</hi> and Aſſtance:</l>
                        <l>Life, Wealth, and every thing was due</l>
                        <l>To Him, who or'e us rul'd,</l>
                        <l>And Whilſt that <hi>Cant</hi> they would purſue,</l>
                        <l>We'd all of's E'en been fool'd,</l>
                        <l>Had not their Church's Lands been thought</l>
                        <l>Belonging to the Throne:</l>
                        <l>And made 'em change their former note,</l>
                        <l>And what they ſaid diſown.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. IX. Of <hi>Iupiter</hi> and the <hi>Monkey.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>JOVE was deſirous once to know</l>
                     <l>What Animal did bear</l>
                     <l>The handſom'ſt <hi>Off-ſpring,</hi> or could ſhow</l>
                     <l>A <hi>little one</hi> moſt fair.</l>
                     <l>He ſummon'd every living thing</l>
                     <l>Unto a certain place,</l>
                     <l>To come before him, and to bring</l>
                     <l>A Pattern of it's Race.</l>
                     <l>Forth with each Female creature came,</l>
                     <l>Which Air, or Sea, or Earth,</l>
                     <l>Could for its proper Tenant claim,</l>
                     <l>And each produc'd a Sample of it's <hi>Birth.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When as the Pow'rful God was juſt</l>
                     <l>Deciding the diſpute,</l>
                     <l>Up to the Throne a <hi>Monkey</hi> thruſt,</l>
                     <l>A moſt deformed Brute!</l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96878:26"/>
                     <l>And with, her <hi>Young one</hi> in her hand</l>
                     <l>(Whilſt All the Company ſmil'd)</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vouchſafe great Jove to underſtand</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mine is the fineſt Child:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pleaſe you my Liege to view this face,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How regular and ſweet!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How well proportion'd every grace!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And how exact the features meet?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Surely my Lord can ne're refuſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Child and Me the Bays.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When Jove for laughing could not <hi>chuſe:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And all of 'em went their ways.</l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>So <hi>Young</hi> Aeſop from <hi>Bath,</hi> or <hi>Old</hi> Aeſop from <hi>Whitehall,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>May amuſe <hi>Town,</hi> and <hi>Country</hi> with a fab'lous recital,</l>
                        <l>And in love with themſelves think their own things <hi>the beſt,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Whilſt the <hi>Clergy,</hi> they laugh at, eſcape the dull <hi>Jeſt:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And all the ſucceſs of each Fable and Story</l>
                        <l>Is to lay down their <hi>own</hi> Faults like the <hi>Monkey</hi> before ye.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. X. Of the <hi>Hares</hi> and the <hi>Frogs.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Time was fix'd when Hares ſhould meet,</l>
                     <l>And for <hi>diſpatch of Buſineſs fit,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Without the leaſt delays,</l>
                     <l>To remedy their preſent State,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe anticipate their Fate,</l>
                     <l>By proper <hi>means</hi> and <hi>ways.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Strait every Puſs the <hi>Form</hi> forſook,</l>
                     <l>Which He or She for ſhelter took,</l>
                     <l>And haſten'd to the place</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96878:27"/>
                     <l>Which by appointment was deſign'd,</l>
                     <l>To heal the miſchiefs of their <hi>Kind</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or make extinct their <hi>Race.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The SPEAKER choſe, and <hi>Members</hi> plac'd,</l>
                     <l>The Houſe reſolv'd it ſelf at laſt</l>
                     <l>Into a grand Commitee:</l>
                     <l>But what a pother, Lord! they kept?</l>
                     <l>One ſigh'd, another trembling wept,</l>
                     <l>'Twould move us all to pity.</l>
                     <l>At length a <hi>Chief</hi> of high Rnown,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Ranger</hi> of ſome mighty <hi>Down,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Firſt ask'd the Houſ's leave:</l>
                     <l>And then ſtood up, whilſt all the reſt</l>
                     <l>With ſorrows, and with grief oppreſs'd</l>
                     <l>Could nothing elſe but grieve.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Brethren,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>a wretched Race,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whom Men and Dogs, and Eagles chaſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Sport of the Creation,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In vain we're thinking to redreſs</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Our Grievances, or make 'em leſs,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>While in this living Station.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hounds will for ever be purſuing,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And Hunters meditating ruin,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whilſt we muſt ſtill be flying;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>We'd better (Friends) if I might give</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Advice, this moment ceaſe to live,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then always be a dying.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Tho' <hi>Death</hi> is not a thing which fuits</l>
                     <l>With conſtitutions of ſuch <hi>Bruits</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>As <hi>Hares</hi> are of, 'tis certain:</l>
                     <l>Yet they reſolv'd, with much ado,</l>
                     <l>To bid the <hi>Groves,</hi> and <hi>Hills</hi> adieu,</l>
                     <l>Tho not 'thout tears at parting.</l>
                     <l>By chance there was a River near</l>
                     <l>The place, where theſe <hi>Aſſemblers</hi> were</l>
                     <l>Debating how to die,</l>
                     <l>Wherefore to put off all delays,</l>
                     <l>They fix'd in that to end their days</l>
                     <l>The ſooner, 'cauſe ſo nigh,</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96878:27"/>
                     <l>But, Lord! how Puſs would backward ſhrink,</l>
                     <l>When almoſt at the very brink,</l>
                     <l>And ſigh ſhe was ſo near!</l>
                     <l>Then tell her Beads, and wiſh ſome <hi>Saint</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Would help her from this damn'd reſtraint,</l>
                     <l>And eaſe her of her fear!</l>
                     <l>At laſt the leading Hares were come,</l>
                     <l>Prepar'd and ready for their Doom,</l>
                     <l>And at the Flood arriving,</l>
                     <l>A Frog or two into it skipp'd,</l>
                     <l>Which made 'em look before they leap'd,</l>
                     <l>And think of longer living.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hark ye (ſaid Puſs who bore the ſway)</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fair and ſoftly wins the Day,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>There's no ſuch need to die yet;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I'll Home again, and e'em ſubmit</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To what my Deſtiny thinks fit,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And keep my Form in quiet.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Troth Sirs, the Fate of</hi> Frogs <hi>is worſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Than</hi> ours, <hi>which we at preſent curſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And are ſo much afraid at;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For me who fear moſt things beſide</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Are fear'd by them, and that's my Pride</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Since theſe are us diſmay'd at.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sirs, it would be a pretty: Jeſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If ſince our life is not the beſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It ſhould be made our loathing.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Faith tho' I cannot be the</hi> Chief,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I have this comfort and relief,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I'm</hi> better far than nothing.</l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>Hence let the Male contented mind</l>
                        <l>Inſtructive Leſſons draw;</l>
                        <l>Not be uneaſy, when confin'd</l>
                        <l>Within the bounds of Law.</l>
                        <l>What tho' his Purſe is ſomething drein'd,</l>
                        <l>For Peace he ne'ere deſir'd,</l>
                        <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96878:28"/>
                        <l>And has in pare that Prince maintain'd</l>
                        <l>Who might have all requir'd?</l>
                        <l>A Neighb'ring King's <hi>beſt</hi> Subjects paid</l>
                        <l>Thrice more than <hi>William's</hi> worſt,</l>
                        <l>And without Mony Laws obey'd,</l>
                        <l>When his with <hi>Mony</hi> curs'd.</l>
                        <l>If therefore he like <hi>Hare</hi> ſhould grieve</l>
                        <l>Since ſmall reſpect we ſhow Him,</l>
                        <l>Like <hi>Hare</hi> in Fable let him live</l>
                        <l>Since he has <hi>Frogs</hi> below him.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:28"/>
                  <p>OLD AESOP At WHITEHAL, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:29"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:29"/>
                  <head>The PREFACE.</head>
                  <p>IT is now the Mode, it ſeems, for Brutes to turn Politicians; and if we may give Credit to ſome late Authors, their Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled at <hi>Tunbridge</hi> and <hi>Bathe.</hi> The Lion who by Preſcription hath been own'd for King, <hi>Nemine Gontradicente,</hi> pleads it as his Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to ſummon them to his Banquetting-Houſe at <hi>Whitehal;</hi> whence all the Three ſttaes may by a ſhort and eaſie Walk arrive together at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and there conſult for the Common Good. He carries a bundle of Arrows in his Hand, with this Motto over them, <hi>Concordia resparvae creſcunt, diſcordia maxima dilabuntur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If there be no <hi>Myſteries in Chriſtianity,</hi> it ſeems there are ſome in <hi>Policy;</hi> when <hi>Jacobites</hi> and <hi>Commonwealths men,</hi> who have mutually branded one another with the harſheſt Names that Malice and Rancour could invent, ſhould now unite in a Deſign againſt the preſent Government, as a common Center. If it be ſo, (which <hi>Old AESOP</hi> is very unwilling to believe,) he hath given Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to his Beaſts, in the following <hi>Fables,</hi> to declare the firſt to be (what they always were) <hi>Knaves,</hi> and the latter (which he is ſure they will be loth to be accounted) <hi>Fools.</hi> If the Reflections ſeem too Satyrical, they may conſider that it comes from Beaſts like themſelves. And ſo <hi>Aeſop</hi> bids them Farewel, but to take Care not to divide the prey till it is caught.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Whitehal,</hi>
                        <date>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temb. <hi>22. 1698.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="summons">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:30"/>
                  <head>THE SUMMONS.</head>
                  <l>THE, Jackall did the King of Brutes inform</l>
                  <l>That ſome deſign'd to mine, and ſome to ſtorm</l>
                  <l>His Royal Fort. At which, with generous Rage</l>
                  <l>The Kingly Beaſt, their Malice to aſſwage,</l>
                  <l>Sends forth his Summons, That they ſhould appear</l>
                  <l>At <hi>Brutes Whitehal,</hi> from Quarters far and near,</l>
                  <l>There to conſult; and if they found that any</l>
                  <l>Better deſerv'd the Sway among the <hi>Many</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Than <hi>Leo</hi> did, he wou'd the Crown forſwear</l>
                  <l>And never henceforth any Scepter bear:</l>
                  <l>But at the ſame time gives't as his Advice,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It's better to fill Bag one time than thrice,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or Three times three. It's better under one,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Than many Maſters, to lament and groan.</hi>
                  </l>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96878:30"/>
                  <head>Old AESOP AT WHITEHAL, GIVING Advice to the Young <hi>AESOPS</hi> AT Tunbridge <hi>and</hi> Bathe.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. I. The <hi>Tortoiſe</hi> and <hi>Frogs.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Heavy <hi>Tortoiſe</hi> ſeeing <hi>Frogs</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nimbly leap in Pools and Boggs,</l>
                     <l>Bleſs'd their limber Hams, that they</l>
                     <l>Could ſo bravely frisk and play;</l>
                     <l>Curs'd the hard and heavy Pack</l>
                     <l>That Nature laid on his own Back:</l>
                     <l>He could neither Skip nor Dance,</l>
                     <l>Nor caper <hi>A-la-mode de France.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But as ſoon's he ſaw the <hi>Stork</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Could the <hi>Frogs</hi> from Puddle fork,</l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96878:31"/>
                     <l>And that for all their nimble Heels</l>
                     <l>They became a Prey to <hi>Eels;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then he quickly chang'd his Note,</l>
                     <l>And for's own Coat of Mail gave Vote;</l>
                     <l>Thank'd his Stars that he was free</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Storks</hi> and ſuch-like Tyranny,</l>
                     <l>By being armed Cap-a-pee.</l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>Did but ſee through <hi>Gallick</hi> Sway</l>
                        <l>How feeble Subjects are a Prey</l>
                        <l>To th' Sovereign's arbitrary Will,</l>
                        <l>Who can at's Pleaſure ſave and kill;</l>
                        <l>Did we feel th' Effects of's Sword and Flames</l>
                        <l>Saw Virgins raviſh'd, heard the Cries of Dames;</l>
                        <l>When Soldiers ſack their Towns, deſtroy their Men,</l>
                        <l>Cut off their Children, ſcarce ſpare One in Ten;</l>
                        <l>Could we but ſee <hi>Rome</hi>'s Prieſts converting <hi>France</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>With Arguments from Gun, Sword, Spear, and Lance;</l>
                        <l>And then reflect that this had been our Doom,</l>
                        <l>Could <hi>James</hi> the Juſt have paid his Von's to <hi>Rome,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>We would not grumble at the Tax we pay</l>
                        <l>To keep ſuch Monſtrous Tyranny away,</l>
                        <l>But ſhould, that <hi>William</hi> might live ever pray.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. II. Of the other <hi>Members</hi> conſpiring againſt the <hi>Belly.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>ONce on a Time the Hands and Feet,</l>
                     <l>With Back, and Loins, and Bum did meet</l>
                     <l>In a Rebellious Conſult, where</l>
                     <l>The B— ch as Speaker took the Chair,</l>
                     <l>And with an uncouth-hollow ſound</l>
                     <l>The following Treaſon did propound:</l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96878:31"/>
                     <l>Brethren, quoth he, you know the Head</l>
                     <l>Makes us toil and ſweat for Bread,</l>
                     <l>Yet nothing to our Lot doth fall,</l>
                     <l>But <hi>idle Gut</hi> conſumes it all.</l>
                     <l>My Friends, if you'll be rul'd by me,</l>
                     <l>We will ſhake off this Tyranny.</l>
                     <l>If Head and Belly will have Meat,</l>
                     <l>Let them toil for't with Hands and Feet.</l>
                     <l>Agreed, ſays Back, I vow and ſwear,</l>
                     <l>For them I'll no more Burthens bear.</l>
                     <l>Content, ſays Bum, if it be your Will;</l>
                     <l>Fot I love dearly to ſit ſtill.</l>
                     <l>Says Feet, I'll no more Errands run.</l>
                     <l>The Loins ſay, Brethren, it is done.</l>
                     <l>The Hands vow they would work no more,</l>
                     <l>And wiſh they'd been as wiſe before.</l>
                     <l>The Members thus in Holy League</l>
                     <l>Did bleſs themſelves for this Intrigue.</l>
                     <l>But ſuddenly the Hands grew weak,</l>
                     <l>The Feet grew numb, the Loins did ſhake,</l>
                     <l>The Back was feeble, the Bum grew poor:</l>
                     <l>And Breech the Chair-man loud did roar,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pray cram the Gut, and we'll rebel no more.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>It's hop'd this will not be forgot</l>
                        <l>By thoſe who form'd the <hi>Tunbridge</hi> Plot;</l>
                        <l>Old <hi>Aeſop</hi> was a Man of Senſe,</l>
                        <l>Such Doctrines never did diſpenſe,</l>
                        <l>That People ſhould refuſe Support,</l>
                        <l>And pine themſelves to ſtarve the Court.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="fable">
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96878:32"/>
                     <head>FAB. III. The <hi>Hermit</hi> and the <hi>Soldier.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Pious <hi>Hermit</hi> ſeeing a Man of Blood</l>
                     <l>Come ſtrutting thro' his ſolitary Wood,</l>
                     <l>Accoſts him thus: Dear Brother, why do you</l>
                     <l>In Human Blood and Gore your Hands imbrue?</l>
                     <l>Leave off that Trade, be 'Partner in my Cell,</l>
                     <l>Read, pray, and think, and ſave your Soul from Hell.</l>
                     <l>The Soldier look'd ſtern,</l>
                     <l>But at laſt did reply,</l>
                     <l>I am wiling to learn,</l>
                     <l>And G—zds I'll comply.</l>
                     <l>We Men of the Sword</l>
                     <l>Are not worth a T —d,</l>
                     <l>But are baſely kept under,</l>
                     <l>Nor have Pay, nor have Plunder.</l>
                     <l>A plague on the Peace</l>
                     <l>Which makes our Gain ceaſe:</l>
                     <l>And ſeeing it is ſo,</l>
                     <l>With the Hermit I'll go,</l>
                     <l>Till the Drums beat again, and the Trumpets do blow.</l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>Juſt ſo the <hi>Jacks</hi> their deſperate Cauſe forſake,</l>
                        <l>And to the ſide o'th' Commonwealth betake;</l>
                        <l>Since their own King has play'd the Foot, and's gone,</l>
                        <l>Ours to moleſt they turn up every Stone.</l>
                        <l>The Church, the Church, is ready to fire,</l>
                        <l>Is all their Out-cry: Brethren, ſave the Quire,</l>
                        <l>Take care a'th' Steeple, Chancel, Surplice, Crape,</l>
                        <l>The Church of <hi>England</hi> Dov's in danger of a Rape,</l>
                        <l>No thanks to them ſhe did from Father <hi>Peter's</hi> ſcape:</l>
                        <l>Yet when their Prince, and's Prieſts ſhall venture over,</l>
                        <l>Theyll ſwear ſhe is no Chaſt nor Turtle Lover,</l>
                        <l>But did to others her fair Breaſts diſcover;</l>
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96878:32"/>
                        <l>Then they will be for Common-wealth no more,</l>
                        <l>But ſcrew Prerogative high as before,</l>
                        <l>Huff like <hi>N—S—r,</hi> crackle like <hi>B—S—wer.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. IV. The <hi>Aſs</hi> in the <hi>Lion</hi>'s Skin.</head>
                     <l>A Certain <hi>Aſs</hi> being ſtruck with Shame</l>
                     <l>Of's native Slavery, and his Name,</l>
                     <l>Made ſhift to ſteal a <hi>Lion</hi>'s Skin,</l>
                     <l>And boldly ſtalk'd about therein;</l>
                     <l>Shook off his innate ſluggiſh Pace,</l>
                     <l>And did aſſume an awful Face,</l>
                     <l>As if h' had been of <hi>Lybian</hi> Bree'd,</l>
                     <l>And from the Baſtinado freed.</l>
                     <l>But's curs'd Ears, and Cathedral Note,</l>
                     <l>To his great Grief, reveal'd the Plot;</l>
                     <l>For when he did attempt to roar,</l>
                     <l>He could not do't, but bray'd juſt as before.</l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>Thus Non-reſiſtance thinks't no Sin</l>
                        <l>To put on a true Patriot's Skin,</l>
                        <l>And plead for Liberty and Laws,</l>
                        <l>And eaſie Tax. But mark, the Cauſe;</l>
                        <l>He would the Government diſable,</l>
                        <l>And loſe the Ship for want, of Cable,</l>
                        <l>And by this means it comes to paſs,</l>
                        <l>We know the old <hi>Paſſive Obedience Aſs.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="fable">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96878:33"/>
                     <head>FAB. V. The <hi>Wolf</hi> and <hi>Hedgehog.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Greedy <hi>Wolf</hi> that ravag'd Hills and Plains,</l>
                     <l>Devour'd the Flocks, and beggar'd all the Swains,</l>
                     <l>Triumph'd and skipp'd. But Plenty, cauſing waſte,</l>
                     <l>At length he knew not where, to break his Faſt;</l>
                     <l>But in his Range meets with a Porcupine,</l>
                     <l>A curious Bit to make, <hi>Lycaon</hi> dine:</l>
                     <l>His eager Chaps would fain been at the Prey,</l>
                     <l>But the arm'd <hi>Hedgehog</hi> held him at a Bay.</l>
                     <l>Hungry <hi>Lycaon</hi> ſeeing this, cries out,</l>
                     <l>My little Brother, how comes this about?</l>
                     <l>Have you forgot the late concluded Peace,</l>
                     <l>That you do ſtill your Armour wear,</l>
                     <l>As if there were new Cauſe of Fear?</l>
                     <l>Lay by your Darts, and let War ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>You cannot think that I will break the League.</l>
                     <l>And Brother-Brutes ſurprize by falſe Intrigue.</l>
                     <l>Nay, Hay, ſays Hedgehog, Brother, I don't ſay</l>
                     <l>That you will me or other Brutes betray;</l>
                     <l>But ne'ertheleſs it doth appear,</l>
                     <l>While you have Tusks, there's Cauſe of Fear:</l>
                     <l>Let me firſt draw your Teeth, and <hi>Sans</hi> Delay,</l>
                     <l>I'll throw my Quiver, and my Darts away.</l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>Thus crafty Jacks do plead our Cauſe,</l>
                        <l>Arm'd Troops in Time of Peace, ſubvert our Laws:</l>
                        <l>Lay down your Arms and then we ſwear,</l>
                        <l>That our brave Prince will ſoon appear;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>La Hogue</hi> you know is very near.</l>
                        <l>But ſince <hi>Van Trump,</hi> and bold <hi>De Rutter,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>With Ball and Powder made ſuch ſplutter,</l>
                        <l>He's as much afraid of Sword and Bomb,</l>
                        <l>As was his Grandſire in his Grandame's Womb.</l>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96878:33"/>
                        <l>Disband your Troops therefore we pray,</l>
                        <l>The Nation cannot bear your Pay.</l>
                        <l>Then come the Wolves o'er from <hi>Campeigne,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And carry all, the Sheep away;</l>
                        <l>Then will our Prince, like <hi>Mars</hi> in warlike Guiſe,</l>
                        <l>Encamp at <hi>Hounſlow</hi> to ſhoot Butterflies.</l>
                        <l>No Man can ſay that he will break the Law,</l>
                        <l>Or us by Standing-Armies over-awe;</l>
                        <l>Since it is clear, as e'er was Light of Sun,</l>
                        <l>His Army never ſtood but always run.</l>
                        <l>Let no foul Tongue our Valorious Prince diſgrace,</l>
                        <l>For he in Perſon always won the Race:</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Boyn</hi>'s fair Flood, and <hi>Sarum</hi>'s ſpacious Plain,</l>
                        <l>Will this great Truth far evermore maintain.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VI. The <hi>Fox</hi> caught in a Trap.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Certain <hi>Fox</hi> being caught in Trap,</l>
                        <l>Did loſe his Tail by the Miſhap.</l>
                        <l>And cried Alas!</l>
                        <l>For, his Diſgrace,</l>
                        <l>He could not ſhew Face,</l>
                        <l>Nor follow the Chaſe:</l>
                        <l>But yet, ſays he, tho' <hi>Reynards</hi> do beguile</l>
                        <l>The other <hi>Brutes</hi> by ſome fly Trick and Wile;</l>
                        <l>I do not know that Foxes are exempted</l>
                        <l>From being fool'd too, if they're fitly tempted.</l>
                        <l>Then let me go try,</l>
                        <l>And briskly apply</l>
                        <l>My Wits, to deceive,</l>
                        <l>And make Foxes believe,</l>
                        <l>That the Burden of their Tail,</l>
                        <l>In Rain, Snow or Hail,</l>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96878:34"/>
                        <l>Is intolerably grievous,</l>
                        <l>And in Hunting Miſchievous.</l>
                        <l>If by this Means I can but prevail,</l>
                        <l>To have every Fox cut off his own Tail,</l>
                        <l>Then none of 'em at me will mock, ſcoff or rail.</l>
                        <l>Away <hi>Reynard</hi> goes,</l>
                        <l>His deſign to propoſe.</l>
                        <l>Says Fathers and Mothers,</l>
                        <l>Dear Siſters and Brothers,</l>
                        <l>Don't flout, jeer and mock,</l>
                        <l>At my mangled Dock:</l>
                        <l>You know that your Tails,</l>
                        <l>But little avails,</l>
                        <l>When you leap over Pales,</l>
                        <l>To catch Sheep and Fowls;</l>
                        <l>Then do not like Owls,</l>
                        <l>Thus burden your Back,</l>
                        <l>By a thing you might lack.</l>
                        <l>How brisk and how fine</l>
                        <l>Am I without mine?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The reſt perceiving what his Motive was;</l>
                        <l>Told him good Brother this will never paſs.</l>
                        <l>When we'r hunted by Dogs,</l>
                        <l>O'er Hills, and through Bogs.</l>
                        <l>On our Tails we do Piſs,</l>
                        <l>And their Chops do not miſs.</l>
                        <l>And this was the cauſe made the Proverb prevail,</l>
                        <l>He hath got a flap with the Fox's Tail,</l>
                        <l>Then ceaſe Brother Fox,</l>
                        <l>If we mangle our Docks.</l>
                        <l>As you do propoſe,</l>
                        <l>We're expos'd to our Foes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>Thus the curs'd Crew who have themſelves undone,</l>
                        <l>And from their Reaſon, Senſe, and Intereſt run,</l>
                        <l>Would gladly have us caught in that ſame Trap;</l>
                        <l>I'll Men would fain have Brethren in miſhap.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="fable">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96878:34"/>
                     <head>FAB. VII. The <hi>Fox</hi> Preaching to the <hi>Sheep.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Ravening Wolf the Sheep-Cotes did invade,</l>
                        <l>And there ſet up his Butcher's Shambles;</l>
                        <l>Where without trouble of Preambles,</l>
                        <l>He kill'd whatever came to hand.</l>
                        <l>A ſturdy Maſtiff by the Farmer laid</l>
                        <l>In the ſame Fold, preſerv'd the Sheep,</l>
                        <l>So that in Safety they could ſleep,</l>
                        <l>And feed, with quite in their Maſters Land.</l>
                        <l>The Fox who us'd with Wolf to diet,</l>
                        <l>And on the tender Lambs to riot;</l>
                        <l>Perceiving this,</l>
                        <l>Says <hi>Monſieur Wolf,</hi> I am not able</l>
                        <l>To live at ſuch an ill-ſpread Table.</l>
                        <l>Were it amiſs,</l>
                        <l>That I ſhould go and tell the Sheep,</l>
                        <l>The Maſtiff Dog that doth them keep</l>
                        <l>Lives on their Blood;</l>
                        <l>That he and's Maſter every Day,</l>
                        <l>With joint conſent divide the Prey,</l>
                        <l>And make the Sheep their Food.</l>
                        <l>Wolf anſwers, <hi>Reynard,</hi> that is good,</l>
                        <l>Go tell the Sheep that they ſhould ceaſe</l>
                        <l>To cloth their Maſter with their Fleece;</l>
                        <l>Except he will his Dog remove,</l>
                        <l>For ſuch a Guard they do not love</l>
                        <l>In time of Peace.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Fox gets in amongſt the Flock,</l>
                        <l>And with ſly Oratry thus ſpoke.</l>
                        <l>Good Men of Mutton.</l>
                        <l>What do ye with this Maſtiff Dog,</l>
                        <l>He is a mercenary Rogue</l>
                        <l>Not worth a Button?</l>
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96878:35"/>
                        <l>For on pretnce of keeping guard,</l>
                        <l>Your Fleſh and Bones are his Reward:</l>
                        <l>Get him caſhier'd.</l>
                        <l>The Wolf and I have ſworn the Peace,</l>
                        <l>And our Hoſtilities muſt ceaſe,</l>
                        <l>Noughts to be fear'd</l>
                        <l>By him, his Maſter in diſguiſe</l>
                        <l>Means o're the Flocks to Tyrannize</l>
                        <l>On my Salvation.</l>
                        <l>As I'm <hi>a true Son of the Church,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I would not leave you in the Lurch,</l>
                        <l>Of ſuch Damnation.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The bleating Herd began ro grumble,</l>
                        <l>For <hi>Raynard</hi>'s Logick, made them ſtumble,</l>
                        <l>And thus they ſaid:</l>
                        <l>In Faith the Wolf and Fox we ſee</l>
                        <l>Are Enemies to Tyranny;</l>
                        <l>Their Council ought to be obey'd.</l>
                        <l>Since <hi>Ned</hi> the Wolf, and <hi>Batt</hi> the Fox,</l>
                        <l>Are our good Friends, than what a Pox</l>
                        <l>Should we be plagu'd with Curs.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>We will no more our Fleeces yield,</l>
                        <l>Nor have our Lambs tore from the Field,</l>
                        <l>Let's to our Zeal add Spurs:</l>
                        <l>And for our Spokeſman chuſe a Ram,</l>
                        <l>Or ſturdy Goat to Swear and Damn.</l>
                        <l>And 'curſe Diſſenters.</l>
                        <l>Our greateſt Dangers from the Whigs,</l>
                        <l>And cauſe they will not pay Tithe Pigs,</l>
                        <l>The Wolf and Fox on them ſhall have Debentures.</l>
                        <l>Content ſays Fox, and there's my Hand,</l>
                        <l>I'll publiſh this in Woolfiſh-land;</l>
                        <l>Farewell dear Sheep.</l>
                        <l>The Wolf and I will guard your Cotes,</l>
                        <l>And pull out the Diſſenters Throats;</l>
                        <l>But unto you our promiſe keep.</l>
                        <l>The Flock by <hi>Renyard</hi> thus perſwaded,</l>
                        <l>That Dog and Farmer them invaded,</l>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96878:35"/>
                        <l>Straight left the Fido.</l>
                        <l>Did thro' the Hills and Valleys ſtray,</l>
                        <l>And from their Guard did run away;</l>
                        <l>Left him to ſtarve for want of pay:</l>
                        <l>But mark the end.</l>
                        <l>The Wolf and Fox, having prevail'd</l>
                        <l>The ſcatter'd Flocks ſtraight they aſſail'd,</l>
                        <l>And did them all in pieces rend.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>It's hop'd the Sheep of <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Who to the Parliament make haſte,</l>
                        <l>The Moral will teach;</l>
                        <l>Which is no more</l>
                        <l>Then the Proverb of Yore.</l>
                        <l>Let the Geeſe look to't when the Fox doth preach.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VII. The Fable of the <hi>Spunge.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Certain Brewer whoſe Liquor of Life,</l>
                     <l>Did frequently amongſt his Servants raiſe ſtrife,</l>
                     <l>Reſolv'd to abridge them, giving each Man his ſhare,</l>
                     <l>Enough to ſuffice but nothing to ſpare:</l>
                     <l>But the Servants reſolving they would not be ſtinted,</l>
                     <l>Put their Wits on the Rack, and this Device minted.</l>
                     <l>They got Gloves of Spunge which they thruſt in the Liquor,</l>
                     <l>And ſqueezing them often ſpent their Naſters Stock quicker:</l>
                     <l>Which the Brewer underſtanding, he ſeiz'd on the Spunges;</l>
                     <l>Made his Servants repay him, and with Actions them ſwinges:</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96878:36"/>
                     <l>Till he had ſqueez'd back his own, and taught them to be true,</l>
                     <l>To leave off their ſlie Cheats, and be content with their Due.</l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>Thoſe that miſapply the Treaſure of the Nation,</l>
                        <l>Ought thus to be ſqueez'd till they make reparation:</l>
                        <l>We may Tax, and pay on, and the King ſtill be poor.</l>
                        <l>If the Hands of his Servants be pitch'd as before.</l>
                        <l>It's the Intereſt of the Nation, our Senate underſtands,</l>
                        <l>That thoſe who touch Caſh ſhould have clean waſhen hands.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. IX. The <hi>Trumpeter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Trumpeter, who by his Fatal Sounds,</l>
                     <l>Provok'd Mankind to mutual Blood and Wounds;</l>
                     <l>Being ta'ne in Field did for his Life implore:</l>
                     <l>I ſound the Charge ſaid he, but do no more.</l>
                     <l>The Conquerour grew enrag'd at this Defence;</l>
                     <l>Replies, baſe Villain, I'll Diſpatch thee hence,</l>
                     <l>Down to the <hi>Stygian</hi> Shades; doſt thou not know</l>
                     <l>That he who counſels Murder, gives the blow.</l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>The Fable hits thoſe who in former Reigns,</l>
                        <l>For love of Faction, or for love of Gains,</l>
                        <l>Did teach our Monarchs a Deſpotick Sway,</l>
                        <l>And damm'd the People that would not obey:</l>
                        <l>Theſe were the Firebrands of the Church and State,</l>
                        <l>And did more Miſchief than <hi>Jack Straw</hi> or <hi>Kett:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>They caus'd the Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, and that brought on the Tax,</l>
                        <l>Then let the weight of't fall on their own Backs;</l>
                        <l>Why ſhould the Peoples Blood and Treaſure pay</l>
                        <l>To reſcue that which Prieſecraft did betray,</l>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96878:36"/>
                        <l>The Prieſts advanc'd the <hi>Popeling</hi> to the Throne;</l>
                        <l>The Prieſts again did force him to be gone;</l>
                        <l>And now the Prieſts, like Turn-coats, as before,</l>
                        <l>Chuſe Jacks for Senate with Canonick Roar:</l>
                        <l>And Churches danger ſlily would infer,</l>
                        <l>From our great King who bravely reſcued her.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. X. The <hi>Lion</hi> and the <hi>Aſs.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>IT once came to paſs,</l>
                     <l>That the Lion and the Aſs,</l>
                     <l>Did meet in a great Conſultation;</l>
                     <l>When the King of the Brutes,</l>
                     <l>To the dulleſt of Mutes,</l>
                     <l>Did ſeriouſly make Application.</l>
                     <l>True <hi>Roger,</hi> quoth he,</l>
                     <l>Do but hearken to me,</l>
                     <l>And I ſwear I will highten thy Fortune.</l>
                     <l>Thou art now a dull Beaſt,</l>
                     <l>But I'll make the High Prieſt,</l>
                     <l>And the reſt ſhall no more dare thee ſport on.</l>
                     <l>Good Soveraign ſay on,</l>
                     <l>Quoth <hi>Roger</hi> anon,</l>
                     <l>For I am quite weary of Slavery:</l>
                     <l>I ſwear by St. <hi>Peter</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If you'l give me a Mitre</l>
                     <l>I'll ſerve you, be't Roguery or Knavery.</l>
                     <l>I thank you, ſays Lion,</l>
                     <l>Thy word I'll rely on;</l>
                     <l>The Service that I then command thee,</l>
                     <l>Is to teach that I muſt govern,</l>
                     <l>Like an Abſolute Sovereign,</l>
                     <l>And that thoſe will be damn'd that withſtand me.</l>
                     <l>Agreed, ſays the Aſs,</l>
                     <l>I will bring it to paſs,</l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96878:37"/>
                     <l>And have paſſive Obedience in faſhion;</l>
                     <l>They ſhall all be call'd Traitors,</l>
                     <l>And Monarchy-haters,</l>
                     <l>From the Pulpits and Desks of the Nation.</l>
                     <l>But it happen'd that the King,</l>
                     <l>Harp'd on another String,</l>
                     <l>And invaded the Rights of the Aſſes.</l>
                     <l>Then <hi>Roger</hi> turn'd tail,</l>
                     <l>'Gainſt his Sovereign did rail,</l>
                     <l>In his Preachments, his Prayers and Glaſſes.</l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>Thus Tyrant Princes did make uſe of Prieſts,</l>
                        <l>Their Subjects to transform from Men to Beaſts.</l>
                        <l>The time's well known, you need not ask me when,</l>
                        <l>But e're from Beaſts they turn to Men again,</l>
                        <l>The Prieſts muſt be reform'd; ſuch Reformation</l>
                        <l>Is th' only Remedy can ſave the Nation.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:37"/>
                  <p>AESOP Return'd from TUNBRIDGE.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:38"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:38"/>
                  <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AESOP,</hi> it ſeems, has been a little diſturb'd of late, and it has been argu'd <hi>Pro &amp; Con,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Virtuoſi,</hi> whether his Indiſpoſition was the effect of <hi>Tunbridge</hi> Waters, or Company. He himſelf has abſolv'd the Waters, and condemn'd the Company, which has oblig'd 'em in their own Juſtification to ſend him to <hi>Bedlam</hi> to have his own Brains ſet right, for endeavouring to rectifie theirs.</p>
                  <p>Since his Retirement two more have ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up from <hi>Bathe</hi> and <hi>Whitehal,</hi> that, like the two <hi>Demerrius</hi>'s in <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> need only be ſeen to diſcover the Impoſture. But to avoid the Fate of their Predeceſſors
<pb facs="tcp:96878:39"/> of <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> they have taken Meaſures very different from his, and to ſave Dr. <hi>Ty—n</hi> the trouble of Purging their Brains, have agreed to carry none about 'em.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon theſe comes yet another; whether with better Title than the former, is a queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, <hi>Reader,</hi> we leave thee to decide. Only I ſhall take the liberty to give thee ſome Hints, for the better Information of thy Judgment. Firſt then as to his Perſon, it has reſemblance enough to Old <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s (or the Pisture of him, at leaſt, at <hi>Planudes,</hi> and others, have drawn it) that had he left any Legitimate Iſſue behind him, Ours might very well plead his Figure in evidence of his Deſcent from the Old <hi>Beau</hi> of <hi>Samos;</hi> and the Poſture and Condition of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellects, make out the Relation betwixt him and the <hi>Bully</hi> of <hi>Tunbridge.</hi> For this confeſſes himſelf out of his Wits when he writ, and t'other, by univerſal Conſent, mad to Write what he writ.</p>
                  <p>But let me whiſper one thing in thy Ear, upon condition of ſecreſy, if thou wilt give me thy Word and Honour not to diſcloſe it to any Body, I'll aſſure thee they were both Mad, and ſo much the fitter for the Task they have undertaken. For who the De—l
<pb facs="tcp:96878:39"/> but a Madman would venture to write Truth at this time of Day? To deal frankly, the Old Fellow before 'em was much ſuch another ſort of Spark. He either had, or thought he had Wit, which is much at one to an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and could never leave ſhewing his Brains, till a parcel of Blockheads knockt 'em out. He took his Hint from the Women of his Time, who did as they do now, every one that cou'd be convinc'd by her Glaſs, that ſhe was no Beauty, ſet up for a Wit; and if ſhe cou'd not pleaſe People with her Face, cou'd vex 'em with her Tongue, which was equivalent as to point of Self-ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For let either Vanity or Malice be gratified, and we are well enough. But as I was ſaying, <hi>Aeſop</hi> imitated the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in that Piece of Cunning; for 'tis apparent he cou'd not the Men, for they have n't learnt that Craft yet to Piece out the Defects of their Perſons with a Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding. But e'ery Hump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back't, Hard-fac'd Scare-crow is dreſs'd up in a Lac'd-Coat and a Long Wig, to ſet off it's Deformity, and make it more gloriouſly Ridiculous; and the fine empty Thing, that Nature made, as the <hi>Chineſe</hi> do their Bawbles, for the Ornament of a Drawing-Room, is perpetually endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring
<pb facs="tcp:96878:40"/> to ſqueeze it ſelf into the Preſs, and labouring in <hi>Dull Madrigal,</hi> or <hi>Scurvy Lampoon,</hi> to expoſe it's own want of Wit, and it's Friend's, and not content with the Reputation of a Fool a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt its Acquaintance, muſt publiſh it in Print to the World.</p>
                  <p>But what's all this, <hi>Reader,</hi> to thee and I, that be ſure have more Wit? Theſe <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s are Perillous Bold Fellows, and have Plaguy Tongues: But what of that? Let the Beaſt that is gall'd, wince; and let thee and I laugh to ſee 'em kick and ſling like <hi>Ralpho</hi>'s Aſs with a Thiſtle un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Tail, 'tis nothing to us, that <hi>have</hi> (as I ſaid before) Wit, then to come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the reach of one's Tongue, or t'others Heels: And ſo I take my leave of thee.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96878:40"/>
                  <head>AESOP Return'd from TUNBRIDGE.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. I. Aeſop <hi>ſent to <hi>Bedlam.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>AESOP o'ercome with Wind and Spleen,</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Tunbridge</hi> ſought relief;</l>
                     <l>In hopes that change of Air, and Scene,</l>
                     <l>Might eaſe him of his Grief.</l>
                     <l>But there ſuch Shoals of Fools he met,</l>
                     <l>And Knaves twice dipt in Grain;</l>
                     <l>Not the fam'd Waters they were at,</l>
                     <l>Cou'd e're take out the Stain.</l>
                     <l>In vain a Friend among the Youth</l>
                     <l>He ſought all <hi>Tunbridge</hi> round;</l>
                     <l>Till ſneaking Solitary <hi>Truth</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>He in a Corner found.</l>
                     <l>Thus met, they readily agree,</l>
                     <l>And did ſtrange Tales deviſe,</l>
                     <l>Lab'ring to make thoſe Coxcombs ſee,</l>
                     <l>That wou'd put out their Eyes.</l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96878:41"/>
                     <l>Till netled at their juſt Reproof,</l>
                     <l>The Knaves and Fools combine;</l>
                     <l>And him, and his Companion both</l>
                     <l>To a dark Room confine.</l>
                     <l>Next Stage, they knew not why nor how,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>London</hi> they were bound:</l>
                     <l>Where both of 'em together now,</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Bedlam</hi> may be found.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In vain we ſtrive Mens Error to correct,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or point out Follies, which themſelves neglect.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fools are a ſtubborn Race, and hard to break</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wiſdom's the only Gift they ſcorn to take;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And he that ſhews his Brains to ſuch a Rout,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Takes a fair way to have 'em beaten out.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wiſe Men in them alone miſtake their Tools,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Knaves only have the skill to manage Fools.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let empty Fops be proud of their Miſhaps,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For he that takes it off, deſerves the Cap.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. II. The <hi>Wolf</hi> and <hi>Porcupine.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Hungry Wolf, that long'd to Dine</l>
                     <l>Upon a well fed Porcupine,</l>
                     <l>Found he had need of all his Skill.</l>
                     <l>To taſte the Fleſh, and ſcape the Quill:</l>
                     <l>And therefore ſlily thus addreſt,</l>
                     <l>In Fawning Terms, the wary Beaſt.</l>
                     <l>What is it Neighbour that you fear?</l>
                     <l>What Enemy? what danger's near?</l>
                     <l>What means this Magazine of Arms,</l>
                     <l>When Treaties ſign'd ſecure from Harms?</l>
                     <l>When all Hoſtilities muſt ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>Why ſuch a Guard in Times of Peace?</l>
                     <l>Why will you now in Safety beat</l>
                     <l>The Burthen, and Expence of War?</l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96878:41"/>
                     <l>To whom the crafty Beaſt reply'd,</l>
                     <l>Theſe are not for Defence but Pride.</l>
                     <l>For truly, Neighbour, as you ſay,</l>
                     <l>They're uſeleſs at this time of Day,</l>
                     <l>And I ſhou'd be of your belief,</l>
                     <l>Cou'd I but ſee you draw your Teeth.</l>
                     <l>Fr—ce <hi>is the wheedling Wolf, 'tis plain,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That gapes for lucious Bit;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And we know who's the Porcupine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But that ſhe wants the Wit.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What need of Fleets, or Armies now,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That once were</hi> E—d's <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aſt?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Fr—ce <hi>to our Articles will bow,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And guard the</hi> Spaniſh <hi>Coaſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let us diſarm our Men of War,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Since ſhe ſuch ſtore equips;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>She'll ſave us that Expence and Care,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And Convoy home our Ships.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Preparations at</hi> Campeign,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And</hi> Breſt, <hi>ſecure our Ports,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They'll ſpare us Fifty Thouſand Men,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To Garriſon our Forts.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. III. The <hi>Fox</hi> and <hi>Grapes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>UPON a luſty Bunch of Grapes,</l>
                     <l>A liquoriſh Fox had fixt his Eyes,</l>
                     <l>Who licking of his wat'ring Chaps,</l>
                     <l>A thouſand Tricks to reach it tries.</l>
                     <l>But all his Wiles in vain aſſay'd,</l>
                     <l>Out of all hopes of getting nigh,</l>
                     <l>What Fool for Unripe Traſh, he ſaid,</l>
                     <l>Would riſque his Neek to clime ſo high?</l>
                     <l>That charming Fruit, (I dare alledge)</l>
                     <l>That looks ſo tempting and ſo fair,</l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96878:42"/>
                     <l>Will ſet ſome Coxcomb's Teeth on edge,</l>
                     <l>Or draw ſome Fool into a Snare.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ambitious Men that miſs their Aim,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>At leaſt affect to be thought Wiſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And court the Popular Eſteem,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By ſeeming honours to diſpiſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thoſe whom the Mob their Patriots call,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Factions and Jealouſies foment;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Masking with Common Good their Gall,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And Publick Zeal their Diſcontent,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To buſie Courts at firſt they throng,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Till vext, and hopeleſs to prevail,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or ſhare in doing of the Wrong,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In Senates th'at Corruption rail,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Courtier or Patriot by turns,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Hypocrite our Patience tries;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diſgrac'd, our Grievances he mourns,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or laughs in place at Jealouſies.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. IV. The <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Pears.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Wanton Sloven of a Prieſt,</l>
                        <l>Invited to a Bridal Feaſt,</l>
                        <l>Under a Hedge upon the Ground,</l>
                        <l>A Hoard of Mellow Pears had found.</l>
                        <l>Theſe were, quoth he, to hungry Sinner,</l>
                        <l>That had no hopes of Wedding-Dinner,</l>
                        <l>Brave tempting Morſels, a rich Prize,</l>
                        <l>Which at this juncture I diſpiſe,</l>
                        <l>Now to more Rarities engag'd,</l>
                        <l>Than e're in <hi>Noah</hi>'s Ark were cag'd;</l>
                        <l>Fiſh, Fowl, Fruit, Sweet-meats to excite,</l>
                        <l>And rouſe a Founder'd Appetite;</l>
                        <l>Therefore ſweet Pears this time, adieu,</l>
                        <l>My Stomach will not ſtoop to you.</l>
                        <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96878:42"/>
                        <l>Yet e're we part we'll have a Jeſt,</l>
                        <l>Then ſcornfully he on 'em Piſt,</l>
                        <l>And cry'd, who e're theſe Pears ſhall eat,</l>
                        <l>He ſhall have Sauce as well as Meat.</l>
                        <l>This done, impatient of delay,</l>
                        <l>He jocundly perſu'd his Way,</l>
                        <l>Moſt happy in Imagination,</l>
                        <l>Chewing the Cud of Expectation.</l>
                        <l>Till to a Brook approaching nigh,</l>
                        <l>By Rains late fallen ſwell'd ſo high,</l>
                        <l>That 'twas impoſſible to paſs;</l>
                        <l>His rumbling Stomach call'd him Aſs.</l>
                        <l>And bid him Ford, or Swim the Flood,</l>
                        <l>And make his vapring Promiſe good,</l>
                        <l>Or, ſpight of all his Scoffs and Jeers,</l>
                        <l>He, Sauce and all, ſhould eat the Pears.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Prieſt, who Belly dearly lov'd,</l>
                        <l>At this Reproach was ſtrangely mov'd;</l>
                        <l>Yet his unhappy caſe was ſuch,</l>
                        <l>He hated Danger full as much.</l>
                        <l>At Diſappointment ſore dejected,</l>
                        <l>He ſadly on the Pears reflected:</l>
                        <l>He was by Word and Honour bound</l>
                        <l>To ſtand to't, and maintain his ground.</l>
                        <l>And now the Pears ſo lovely grew,</l>
                        <l>That Water from both ends they drew.</l>
                        <l>He therefore all his cunning Bent,</l>
                        <l>To find out ſome Expedient,</l>
                        <l>To prove himſelf this once miſtaken,</l>
                        <l>And ſave his Credit and his Bacon.</l>
                        <l>Inward he turn'd his ſullen Looks,</l>
                        <l>And romaging o're all his Books,</l>
                        <l>He met an ancient Convocation,</l>
                        <l>That funiſh'd him with an Evaſion.</l>
                        <l>Quoth he, they cou'd not be my due,</l>
                        <l>Nor might I ſeize 'em till I knew,</l>
                        <l>And Providence had time to prove,</l>
                        <l>This heap of Pears was <hi>Treaſure trouve;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96878:43"/>
                        <l>But now I plainly underſtand,</l>
                        <l>They truly are a <hi>Deodand;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And he that Abdicates 'em here,</l>
                        <l>Has loſt all Title to one Pear.</l>
                        <l>And I ſhould be a Fool no doubt,</l>
                        <l>Shou'd I ſtand any longer out.</l>
                        <l>As for the Stain I caſt on theſe,</l>
                        <l>My ſelf can wipe it off with eaſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. V. The <hi>Aſs</hi> and <hi>Spaniel.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Weary <hi>Aſs</hi> under his Pack,</l>
                        <l>Stood ty'd up to an empty Rack,</l>
                        <l>And ſpy'd a <hi>Spaniel</hi> brisk, and gay,</l>
                        <l>As in his Maſter's lap he lay,</l>
                        <l>That frisk'd about, and had the grace</l>
                        <l>To climb his Shoulders, lick his Face,</l>
                        <l>was always plentifully fed,</l>
                        <l>And from his hand receiv'd his Bread.</l>
                        <l>Hard difference betwixt, quoth he.</l>
                        <l>That happy, idle <hi>Cur,</hi> and Me.</l>
                        <l>He daily is with Dainties ſerv'd,</l>
                        <l>While I, that drudge for all, am ſtarved.</l>
                        <l>But ſince he thrives ſo well by Play,</l>
                        <l>I'le try my Fortune the ſame way.</l>
                        <l>Thus having form'd his Reſolution,</l>
                        <l>He waits a time for Execution.</l>
                        <l>Which found, erecting Tail, and Ears,</l>
                        <l>On Hinder-Feet himſelf he rears,</l>
                        <l>His Fore-Feet on his Maſter lays,</l>
                        <l>And with his Tongue beſmears his Face.</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Man,</hi> who gueſs'd not his intent.</l>
                        <l>Nor dreamt of ſuch a Compliment,</l>
                        <l>Surpriz'd, and vext, and half afraid,</l>
                        <l>To Servants calls aloud for aid,</l>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96878:43"/>
                        <l>To help him to correct th' Offence,</l>
                        <l>And ſore chaſtiſe this Inſolence.</l>
                        <l>And ſince <hi>Aſs</hi> was ſo rampant grown</l>
                        <l>He bids 'em take his Commons down;</l>
                        <l>And henceforth bare Subſiſtance pay</l>
                        <l>Of half Allowance e're day.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The <hi>Aſs</hi> thus mortify'd, and ſore,</l>
                        <l>Vext for his Bones, but Belly more,</l>
                        <l>Cry'd, What a ſtupid Sor am I,</l>
                        <l>My Talent thus to miſapply?</l>
                        <l>Who only for a Drudge am fit,</l>
                        <l>And yet muſt ſet up for a Wit.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Art may refine, and finiſh Nature's Fool,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But no</hi> Buffoon <hi>ſucceeds, that goes by Rule;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For Fooling prettily's a Gift of Nature's,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That ſits but aukwardly on Imitators.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The lively, airy</hi> Marmouſet, <hi>as ſoon</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>May be out-frolickt by the grave</hi> Baboon,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>As Nature by dull</hi> Mimicks <hi>of the Town.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If Squirrel</hi> D—y <hi>frisk on his Beholders,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Muſt the Aſs</hi> Gild—n <hi>ramp upon their Shoulders,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If</hi> Congreve <hi>flatter'd</hi> M —nt—gue <hi>before,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Muſt be by</hi> Gild—n <hi>too be ſlaver'd o're?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>No <hi>wonder Sots, when we this Clod careſs,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Preſume to claim the Dues of neat Addreſs.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Such Poets ſhou'd at</hi> Weſtminſter <hi>untruſs,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And there receive the meed of</hi> Chaerilus;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Yet I cou'd ſpare the Sot, whoe're repines.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cou'd he like him produce but ſeven good Lines.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But he expects Rewards, to blaze our Shame,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For daring to buffoon a mighty Name.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Let others judge, if he deſerves the Rod,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Who treats his Patron worſe eve'n than his God.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What other Names will this vile Wretch blaſpheme?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For 'tis a Libel to be prais'd by him.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But he now feels the Fate he does deſerve,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And knows already what it is to ſtarve.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96878:44"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Henceforth, ye Great, tender your Reputations,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Your Honours ſuffer by ſuch Dedications</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>With Juſtice we may pay for</hi> Kneller<hi>'s hand,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But who at Charges wou'd on Sign-poſts ſtand?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If then the Author's dull to ſuch degree,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>How ſtupid muſt the Sol that pays him be?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VI. The <hi>Graſhopper</hi> and the <hi>Ant.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A <hi>Graſhopper</hi> once thus accoſted an <hi>Ant.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>You know, Sir, what we Men of Quality want,</l>
                        <l>'Tis the Favor to lend me ſome Grains of your Store,</l>
                        <l>For, Faith, at this minute, I am very poor.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>This Summer's Expences have drawn me ſo low,</l>
                        <l>I can ſcarce in the Park make my Figure, I vow.</l>
                        <l>This comes on't, reply'd the frugal grave <hi>Citt,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>When Extravagance only's the meaſure of Wit.</l>
                        <l>Had your Parents but bred you to Buſineſs, your Parts</l>
                        <l>Might have got an Eſtate, now you have your Deſerts.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Says the <hi>Graſhopper,</hi> what wou'd you have me to do,</l>
                        <l>I'm not made for Work, beſides I'm a <hi>Bean;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I Sing, and I Dance, and all the fine Weather.</l>
                        <l>I'm at <hi>Epſom</hi> or <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> or <hi>Bath,</hi> chuſe you whether</l>
                        <l>Ask all the <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>u Monde,</hi> and the <hi>Ladies</hi> if e're</l>
                        <l>They had Muſick, or Ball, if I was not there.</l>
                        <l>E'ry Evening I my Compliment made.</l>
                        <l>And treated with many a fine Serenade.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>'Tis pity the <hi>Ladies,</hi> quoth <hi>Ant,</hi> not to rally,</l>
                        <l>Don't commiſerate one, Sir, of your <hi>belle taillè,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Your Youth, nor Eſtate neither of 'em can tarry,</l>
                        <l>Look Sharp, Sir, about for a <hi>Fortune,</hi> and Marry,</l>
                        <l>For Trading's ſo dead, and our Taxes ſo hard,</l>
                        <l>Not a Farthing can out of our Buſineſs be ſpar'd</l>
                        <l>But comfort! The <hi>Fleet,</hi> or <hi>King's-Bench,</hi> if you ask it,</l>
                        <l>Will find you a Lodging, and Meat from the Basket.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96878:44"/>
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>Fops that would ſtarve far want of Senſe,</l>
                        <l>Petticoat Refugees,</l>
                        <l>Ought much to thank that Providence,</l>
                        <l>Which made 'em Women pleaſe.</l>
                        <l>Swarms that had Rotted in Jayl.</l>
                        <l>Yet want Senſe to pay</l>
                        <l>Thanks to that Smock that was their Bail,</l>
                        <l>But throw't like a Rag away.</l>
                        <l>Yet luckleſs thouſands ſtill contrive</l>
                        <l>To ſpread like Butterflies,</l>
                        <l>That like Beau <hi>Atkinſon</hi> muſt liue,</l>
                        <l>Or like Beau <hi>Norton</hi> die,</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VII. The <hi>Aſs</hi> and <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A <hi>Gard'ner</hi> had a lazy <hi>Aſs</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That hated a hard working place,</l>
                     <l>And offer'd his Petition</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Jove,</hi> with many a Sigh, and Groan,</l>
                     <l>Which mov'd him by continu'd moan</l>
                     <l>To pity his Condition,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Jove,</hi> when his unjuſt pray'r had heard,</l>
                     <l>Next to a <hi>Potter</hi> him preferr'd;</l>
                     <l>At which in Conſternation,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Aſs</hi> once more in doleful Dumps,</l>
                     <l>Falling again upon his Stumps,</l>
                     <l>Renews his Supplication.</l>
                     <l>Grant me my Suit once more, Great <hi>Jove</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Says he, I'll ask no third remove,</l>
                     <l>From any third Diſaſter;</l>
                     <l>What e're you order, I'm content</l>
                     <l>To undergo the Puniſhment</l>
                     <l>Of any other Maſter.</l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96878:45"/>
                     <l>Oh! cou'd You but this Grace afford!</l>
                     <l>The God ſtraight took him at his word,</l>
                     <l>And plac'd him with a <hi>Tanner;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The <hi>Aſs</hi> grown wiſe, when 'twas too late,</l>
                     <l>Bewails his Folly, and his Fate,</l>
                     <l>In lamentable manner.</l>
                     <l>What with the <hi>Gard'ner</hi> did I lack,</l>
                     <l>My Belly-full, at eaſe my Back?</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Potter</hi> gave me: quarter.</l>
                     <l>But this third Service I am in,</l>
                     <l>Will ſtrip me of my very Skin,</l>
                     <l>And make me Folly's Martyr.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A murmuring Mind is ne'r content,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With any ſort of Government;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And Princes ſtrive in vain to pleaſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such reſtleſs Sp'rits as know no eaſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When Taxes make Malecontent,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whom Wealth, and Pow'r, made Inſolent;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What Meaſures muſt a Ruler take,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To ſpare his Back, and ſave his Neck?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In vain they kick at Slavery,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Who grudge the charge of being free.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VIII. The <hi>Owl</hi> and <hi>Bat.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Fierce diſpute 'twixt Birds of Night</l>
                        <l>Aroſe about their <hi>Gifts,</hi> and <hi>Light;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The <hi>Owl</hi> and <hi>Bat</hi> aloud contended,</l>
                        <l>Which was by Nature beſt befriended,</l>
                        <l>Wrangling with clamorous Conteſt</l>
                        <l>Which ſaw the cleareſt, and the beſt;</l>
                        <l>Till from high Words, and angry Speeches,</l>
                        <l>They came to Perſonal Reproaches.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Quoth <hi>Madge,</hi> inſulting o're the <hi>Bat.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>What wou'd this <hi>Flitter-Mouſe</hi> be at?</l>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96878:45"/>
                        <l>Thou Mungrel Vermine art at moſt,</l>
                        <l>And but half Bird thy ſelf canſt boaſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The <hi>Bat</hi> reply'd with indignation,</l>
                        <l>Make to your ſelf the Application;</l>
                        <l>You're ſome Beaſt's Baſtard it appears,</l>
                        <l>As I'll demonſtrate by your Ears.</l>
                        <l>But what is this to our Diſpute,</l>
                        <l>If I am <hi>Vermine,</hi> you're a <hi>Brute.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Then let's agree, the <hi>Owl</hi> reply'd,</l>
                        <l>And by the <hi>Sun</hi> our Cauſe betry'd.</l>
                        <l>A <hi>Nightingale</hi> that hard by ſate,</l>
                        <l>Thus undertook to Arbitrate:</l>
                        <l>How ſhall the <hi>Sun</hi> decide your Caſe,</l>
                        <l>When neither can endure his Face?</l>
                        <l>You've ſaid enough of <hi>Bats</hi> and <hi>Owls,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To prove both purblind Knaves and Fools.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The</hi> Bats, <hi>and</hi> Owls, <hi>of</hi> Pinner's-Hall,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This Fable may apply;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Theſe</hi> Night-Birds <hi>repreſenting all</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The</hi> Paſtors, <hi>and their Fry.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If any wou'd know, whom they fit,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Their Contraverſies read;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And ſee how oft the Sticks are ſplit,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To break each other's Head,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But let 'em not the Truth come near,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nor venture into Light;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For He that does barefac'd appear,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Will ſhew a Hypocrite.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>While they againſt each other bawl,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>They the whole World convince.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And plainly ſhew their wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t to all</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of Faith, as well as Senſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="fable">
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96878:46"/>
                     <head>FAB. IX. <hi>Sharpers</hi> and <hi>Cullies.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>TWo <hi>Sharpers</hi> once to Gameing fell,</l>
                     <l>In a large Company;</l>
                     <l>And manag'd their Intrigue ſo well,</l>
                     <l>They drew in Standers by.</l>
                     <l>They wrangl'd, quarrel'd, and call'd names,</l>
                     <l>And play'd with ſo much heat;</l>
                     <l>That no one jealous of a ſham,</l>
                     <l>Suſpected 'twas a Cheat,</l>
                     <l>But when the Gameſters num'rous grew,</l>
                     <l>And ſtore of Cullies came;</l>
                     <l>Each from the other took his cue,</l>
                     <l>To manage right his Game.</l>
                     <l>A long time doubtful was the Scale,</l>
                     <l>The odds uncertain were;</l>
                     <l>For they do all by turns prevail.</l>
                     <l>And none great loſers are.</l>
                     <l>Till e'ry one at length was dipt,</l>
                     <l>And mighty ſumms were laid;</l>
                     <l>The wink, one of the <hi>Jugglers</hi> tipt,</l>
                     <l>And ſo the Cheat betray'd.</l>
                     <l>But this diſcovery came to late,</l>
                     <l>For now the Game was wone;</l>
                     <l>An empty Pocket was their Fate,</l>
                     <l>And all the Fools undone.</l>
                     <l>Ex— B-nk, <hi>and the</hi> Exchange,</l>
                     <l>Eaſt-Indians <hi>Old and New,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And all the World this very Game,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Too buſily purſue.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Notes, Bills and Stock, and Actions fall,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or without Reaſon riſe;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Juſt as the Jugglers at</hi> Wh—hal,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or</hi> M—cer's Chappel <hi>pleaſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96878:46"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The great One's have Sham fallings out,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To draw the Leſſer in;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But the true Quarrel is, not who,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But how much each ſhall win.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And when the ſmall One's give their Voice,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Who ſhall be moſt Empowr'd;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They have but Liberty of Choice,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By whom they'l be devour'd.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. X. The <hi>Wolf</hi> and <hi>Dog.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Half famiſht <hi>Wolf</hi> met a jolly fat Dog,</l>
                     <l>That was let out for Air, and free'd from th' Clog.</l>
                     <l>Quoth <hi>Iſgrim,</hi> Friend <hi>Towzer,</hi> thou haſt what I lack,</l>
                     <l>How com'ſt thou by all this good Fleſh on thy back?</l>
                     <l>Says <hi>Towzer,</hi> I lodge, and am fed at <hi>Wh—hal,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I live like a Prince, and do nothing but bawl.</l>
                     <l>You live like a Felon, by paltry Sheep-ſtealing,</l>
                     <l>But if you'l be rul'd, and uſe double-dealing,</l>
                     <l>I'll help you to mighty Preferment at C—rt.</l>
                     <l>And you ſhall pay nothing, but Flattery for't.</l>
                     <l>Quoth <hi>Iſgrim,</hi> I like the Conditions ſo well,</l>
                     <l>I long till I'm there, for I ſoon ſhou'd excel;</l>
                     <l>I can cringe like a <hi>Beau,</hi> and humour <hi>My Lord,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And praiſe e'ry foppiſh Nonſenſical word.</l>
                     <l>'Tis enough, ſays the <hi>Cur;</hi> ſo onward they jogg'd.</l>
                     <l>Till <hi>Towzer,</hi> who often was collar'd and clogg'd,</l>
                     <l>Like a <hi>Cur</hi> of good Manners in bowing betray'd</l>
                     <l>The Ring on his Neck, which the Collar had made.</l>
                     <l>Says the crafty fly <hi>Wolf,</hi> in that Circle ſome Spell</l>
                     <l>I ſuppoſe is contain'd, by which you live well.</l>
                     <l>'Tis only, ſays <hi>Towzer,</hi> ne'r mind it I pray,</l>
                     <l>Some looſe hair my Collar has fretted away.</l>
                     <l>Says <hi>Iſgrim,</hi> I owe you, Sir, thanks for this gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e,</l>
                     <l>But if there's a Collar, that alters the caſe.</l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96878:47"/>
                     <l>I'll purchaſe my Place by by no ſuch ſubmiſſion,</l>
                     <l>But forrage the Woods, and not alter Condition.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Wealth, and the Pow'r of great Places pleaſe all,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Who wou'd ſhun the Fatigue, they're encumber'd withall.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They wou'd have the Profit without the Attendance,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſhift of the burden of ſlaviſh dependance.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But here they may ſee by the</hi> Wolf, <hi>and the</hi> Dog,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They that will have the Fat, muſt ſubmit to the Clog.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. XI. Falſe <hi>Piety.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>A Sick Man lay at point of Death,</l>
                        <l>Juſt ready to reſign his Breath.</l>
                        <l>Hard by the Bed his tender Wife</l>
                        <l>Stood, weeping, with Outrageous Grief;</l>
                        <l>Waiting the Moment that ſhould ſix,</l>
                        <l>And make her his Executrix.</l>
                        <l>She wrung her Hands, and tore her Hair,</l>
                        <l>And put up many a fervent Prayer.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Will Cruel</hi> Death, ſhe raving cry'd,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>No other Way be ſatisfy'd?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Oh! will ye on no Terms relent?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Will he take no Equivalent?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>So far below thee Life I prize,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I'll be thy willing Sacrifice.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Remorſleſs</hi> Death, <hi>attend my Call,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Who thy devoted Victim fall.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>All this, <hi>Death</hi> was at hand, and heard;</l>
                        <l>Obey'd the Summons, and appear'd.</l>
                        <l>The Wife, who thought of nothing leſs,</l>
                        <l>Confounded at his Readineſs.</l>
                        <l>Surpriz'd, amaz'd, and Terrify'd,</l>
                        <l>Straight ſnatch'd the Candle up, and cry'd;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pray, let me light you, Sir; I know</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Your Errand, and will wait on you.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96878:47"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>My Husband's Time; alas! is come,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And he lies ready in the Room:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>His Doctors too have done you Wrong,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To keep him from you, here, thus long.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>Where Int'reſt rules, and Profit lies at Stake,</l>
                        <l>All ſorts of People large Profeſſions make.</l>
                        <l>But, as in Trade, when Men on Credit buy,</l>
                        <l>The Wiſe ſiſpect their Pay that bid too high:</l>
                        <l>So in all Obligations that include</l>
                        <l>More than a Favour's worth in Gratitude,</l>
                        <l>Falſe we conclude, or raſh the Vows they make;</l>
                        <l>And only upon Force their Words we take.</l>
                        <l>So have we known, not many Ages ſince,</l>
                        <l>By Sham-Careſſes, a deluded Prince</l>
                        <l>Indulge his Foes; and to their Meaſures yield,</l>
                        <l>Wo did his Ruin on his Favour build.</l>
                        <l>We know, when Words were wanting to expreſs</l>
                        <l>The Timpany of Zeal in each Addreſs,</l>
                        <l>The Trifles Blood and Treaſure, to a Drop,</l>
                        <l>Devoted were, and daily offer'd up:</l>
                        <l>The crouded <hi>Gazettes</hi> did a loud proclaim</l>
                        <l>The hollow Promiſes, that thronging came</l>
                        <l>But when his Wants their real Aid requir'd,</l>
                        <l>And he their boaſted Services deſir'd,</l>
                        <l>Th' <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngrateful Vipers luſty grown, and ſtrong,</l>
                        <l>The Boſom, in Return, that warm'd 'em, ſtung;</l>
                        <l>Happy was he that firſt could get away,</l>
                        <l>And him, they promis'd to ſupport, betray.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="fable">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96878:48"/>
                     <head>FAB. XII. The <hi>Wolf</hi> turn'd <hi>Preacher.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Wolf, whom Health and Strength had left,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Was fallen into Want;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Unable to ſubſiſt on Theft,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Reſolv'd to be a Saint.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In a ſhort Cloak, and little Band,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The New-converted Preacher,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By Means of Formal Tone, and Cant,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Was grown a famous Teacher.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shoals of the Mob he daily caught,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With Sin-confounding Texts, Sirs:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>No precious, painful Brother taught</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>More Edifying Lectures.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>At length a Rake-Hell of the Wood,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That had found out his Haunt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cry'd,</hi> Thou wilt make, Old <hi>Ne'er be Good,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Devil of a Saint.</l>
                     <l>Come, lay the Maſquerade aſide,</l>
                     <l>And let your Comrade know</l>
                     <l>What Roguery you hide,</l>
                     <l>That's worth Transforming ſo.</l>
                     <l>Oh! <hi>quoth the Old Apoſtate</hi> Wolf,</l>
                     <l>Thy lewd Dicentious Ear</l>
                     <l>Is ſcarce yet ſanctifi'd enough,</l>
                     <l>Theſe precious Truths to hear.</l>
                     <l>Like you I rang'd at large; and none</l>
                     <l>More rampant was, while young:</l>
                     <l>But now my Teeth and heels are gone,</l>
                     <l>I For age with my Tongue.</l>
                     <l>I wheedle, flatter, cant, and pray;</l>
                     <l>Deſſemble, fawn, and lye:</l>
                     <l>The ſily Rout think all I ſay</l>
                     <l>Meer Goſpel-Verity.</l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96878:48"/>
                     <l>To me all truſt; both Young, and Old;</l>
                     <l>Smooth Kids, and tender Lambs:</l>
                     <l>I have the Culling of the Fold,</l>
                     <l>And milking of the Dams.</l>
                     <l>You may perchance a Lamb ſurprize;</l>
                     <l>But if you ſhould be ſeen,</l>
                     <l>The pariſh, with their Curs, would riſe,</l>
                     <l>And ſtrip you of your Skin.</l>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>Let empty Fops of Play-houſe Conqueſt vaunt,</l>
                        <l>And toaſt the Laſs that did the Favour grant:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Beau</hi>'s may by vain, and feign'd Intrigues recite;</l>
                        <l>But the true Letcher, is, the Hypocrite.</l>
                        <l>And <hi>B—g-ſs,</hi> in his Tub, debauches more</l>
                        <l>Than ever <hi>Meggs</hi> did on that Spot before.</l>
                        <l>The godly have the Gifts, the Wicked want;</l>
                        <l>For Scandal only's ſinful in a Saint.</l>
                        <l>Thy Maids their brawny Paſtour's Silence truſt;</l>
                        <l>And make them Heroes in Records of Luſt.</l>
                        <l>For this <hi>Moor-Feilds</hi> and <hi>Tunbridge</hi> muſt be priz'd;</l>
                        <l>But <hi>Cr—o, B—ll</hi> and <hi>Wallis</hi> Canoniz'd.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. XIII. The <hi>Satyr</hi> and the <hi>Traveller.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg n="1">
                        <head>I.</head>
                        <l>TO his poor Cell a <hi>Satyr</hi> led</l>
                        <l>A <hi>Traveller,</hi> with Cold half dead;</l>
                        <l>And with great Kindneſs treated:</l>
                        <l>A Fire, Noſe-high, he made him ſtraight;</l>
                        <l>Show'd him his Elbow-Chair of State,</l>
                        <l>And near the Chimney ſeated.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96878:49"/>
                        <head>II.</head>
                        <l>His tingling Hands the <hi>Stranger</hi> blows;</l>
                        <l>At which the <hi>Satyr</hi> wond'ring, roſe,</l>
                        <l>And humbly ask'd the Reaſon.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sir,</hi> quoth the Man, <hi>I mean no Harm;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I only do't, my Hands to warm,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In this Cold, Froſty Seaſon.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <head>III.</head>
                        <l>The <hi>Satyr</hi> gave him, from the Pot,</l>
                        <l>A meſs of Porridge, piping hot:</l>
                        <l>The Man blow'd o'er his Grewel.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What's that for, Friend?</hi> the <hi>Satyr</hi> cry'd.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To cool my Broth,</hi> his <hi>Gueſt</hi> reply'd:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And Truth, Sir, is a Jewel.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="4">
                        <head>IV.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>How!</hi> quoth his <hi>Host; Then is it ſo?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And can you Contradictions blow?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Turn out, and leave my Cottage.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This honeſt Manſion ne'er ſhall hold</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Such Raſcals as blow</hi> Hot <hi>and</hi> Cold:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The De'il muſt find you Pottage.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <div type="moral">
                        <head>MORAL.</head>
                        <l>The C—'s deſir'd, that in their next Choice.</l>
                        <l>They'd be pleas'd, from this <hi>Fable,</hi> to take good Advice:</l>
                        <l>For a man that two <hi>Churches</hi> at once has in view,</l>
                        <l>Shams both in their turns, and to neither is true.</l>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:49"/>
                  <p>AESOP AT AMSTERDAM.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:50"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:50"/>
                  <head>Epiſtle Dedicatory, TO <hi>Old</hi> AESOP <hi>at</hi> Whitehal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>FATHER,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WHERE the Devil have you been all this while? It is now ever ſince the fifty fourth <hi>Olympiad</hi> you dy'd at <hi>Delphos,</hi> and to ariſe again at <hi>Whitehal</hi> is very remarkable. I am now apt to believe the Doctrine of <hi>Tranſmigration,</hi> and that your Soul having paſt the Habitations of the Bodies of the Horſe, the Aſs, and other Beaſts, you'r now informing the Body of a Courtier. Good Dad! don't come too near me, you ſtink moſt damnably of Sulphur, I'm almoſt ſuffocated. You have been lamentably paid off in t'other Country; your Clothes are horridly bedawb'd with liquid Bitumen, Links, Flambeaux and Card-matches; you make a very indifferent Figure indeed Father. What Country you have been in I can't tell, but by your new Fables I find you have liv'd under a Monarchical Government, and are mightily in love with it, as are my Two elder Brothers of <hi>Tunbridge</hi> and <hi>Bathe;</hi> but you youngeſt Son, my Right Worſhipful ſelf, begs your Pardon if he don't jump with you and the reſt of his Brethren in their Notions of Government. You can't
<pb facs="tcp:96878:51"/> tell, Father, what a lamentable ſpot of work you have made with the Fables you wrote the firſt time you liv'd; the ſower <hi>Pedagogues</hi> have made the blind Cheeks of many a Boy as raw as a piece of Beef, becauſe they could not underſtand 'em; nay I have been perſecuted my ſelf upon the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. Beſides, <hi>Sir,</hi> your Fables have been the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of abundance of Lies; your Book ſerves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Charter to the Mythologiſts of all Ages; you ſtand in competition even with the Devil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which ſhall be the reputed Father of Liars. And one would think after you had ſlept ſo many Years, your Conſultation with your Pillow might have afforded you better Thoughts. 'Tis pity, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you and I ſhould fall out after ſo long abſence; but you ought to allow us that live upon the ſurface of the Terreſtrial Globe, to ſee farther than you, who have been ſo many Years embowel'd in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns of the Earth: Indeed, Father, I would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you to return home again unleſs you had brought better Notions with you from t'other Country; for thoſe poſſeſt with your Notions here, we eſteem either Stupid or Mad. Now being in this place, Father, and breathing in a free Air, I can talk of nothing but Freedom, Liberty and Property, I hope, if it does offend the Aſſertors of Tyranny, they'll conſider I am in a common Aſylum, and out of their reach.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>AMSTERDAM</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96878:51"/>
                  <head>AESOP AT AMSTERDAM.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. I. The <hi>Summons.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>THE mighty <hi>Puſs,</hi> not long ſince rul'd the State,</l>
                     <l>Beneath a loneſom Furzbuſh purring ſat;</l>
                     <l>Stroak'd her long Smellers, and rejoic'd to ſee</l>
                     <l>Her awful Picture in her Progeny:</l>
                     <l>Mean while her Kitlings dance before her face,</l>
                     <l>And toſs, like trembling Mice, the Roots of Graſs.</l>
                     <l>Not one amongſt 'em but a Claw does wear,</l>
                     <l>Fit a Monarchic Tyrant Rat to tear.</l>
                     <l>The Good old Cauſe inform'd the Mother's Breaſt,</l>
                     <l>Darts through their Eyes, is by their mein expreſt.</l>
                     <l>Such, ſuch the antient Race of Heroes were,</l>
                     <l>Who did their Rights before their Lives prefer.</l>
                     <l>She calls one to her, of the eldeſt brood;</l>
                     <l>Doſt know, ſaid ſhe, how drown'd in native Blood</l>
                     <l>My Country lies? how the wild Boars invade</l>
                     <l>The Land, and deſart have my Country laid?</l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96878:52"/>
                     <l>'Tis true, I once did eaſe 'em of their Pain;</l>
                     <l>But they, like Fools, embrac'd again the Chain;</l>
                     <l>Wear thoſe dull Fetters I ſo kindly broke,</l>
                     <l>And halt, like Slaves, beneath the ſervile Yoke.</l>
                     <l>Once more I'll try, if my Advice may prove</l>
                     <l>Succeſsful, once exert my antient Love;</l>
                     <l>Summon the Slaves to meet at <hi>Whitehal</hi> Gate,</l>
                     <l>Beneath the Scaffold where I whilom ſate,</l>
                     <l>And puniſh Tyranny, the worſt of Crimes;</l>
                     <l>A juſt example unto future Times.</l>
                     <l>Young <hi>Puſs</hi> the Meſſage takes, and bids fair warning</l>
                     <l>To all the Slaves t'appear the next Morning.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. II. <hi>The Interview.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THE Morning come, the Slaves await,</l>
                        <l>And flock like Bees 'bout <hi>Whitehal</hi> Gate.</l>
                        <l>Some yoak'd, like Country Hogs appear;</l>
                        <l>Others confounded Fetters wear,</l>
                        <l>And ſome moſt horrid Burdens bear.</l>
                        <l>Thus loaded, thus enſlav'd, oppreſt;</l>
                        <l>Nature, 'tis ſtrange, don't call for reſt:</l>
                        <l>Tho legs are gall'd, and ſhouldiers ſore,</l>
                        <l>The bulky Slaves ſtill crave for more:</l>
                        <l>And not an Ideot of the Town</l>
                        <l>Has ſenſe to lay his Burden down.</l>
                        <l>Strait <hi>Puſs</hi> in majeſty appears,</l>
                        <l>Mounting the Scaffold, pricks her Ears,</l>
                        <l>Shakes her Majeſtick Head, aloud</l>
                        <l>She thus beſpoke the num'rous Crowd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I have deſerted long the nauſeous Town,</l>
                        <l>Mourning my Country's Ruin, and my own</l>
                        <l>Expos'd to Tyranny, whilſt Beaſts of prey</l>
                        <l>Ravage my Fields, and ſteal my Lambs away.</l>
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96878:52"/>
                        <l>My Free-born Subjects now are forc'd to bear</l>
                        <l>Loads, which more fit for backs of Camels are;</l>
                        <l>You well deſerve the Fetters you do wear.</l>
                        <l>You under heavy iron Shakels pine,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe Fathers did in glorious Armour ſhine,</l>
                        <l>Thro' fields of Blood to Freedom cut their way,</l>
                        <l>And taught the proudeſt Tyrants to obey;</l>
                        <l>By me ſupported, potent Tyrants fell</l>
                        <l>A Sacrifice to their juſt Cauſe and Hell;</l>
                        <l>No more, no more their ſacred Linage ſtain,</l>
                        <l>No more their Name in your curſt Race profane.</l>
                        <l>Let not their Off-ſpring ſuch Alliance have,</l>
                        <l>Shakles were ne're the Trophies of the Brave;</l>
                        <l>They could wide Conqueſts, and juſt Honours boaſt,</l>
                        <l>But you, dull Slaves! have all your Freedom loſt.</l>
                        <l>Where e're a Tyrant rais'd his impious Head,</l>
                        <l>Strait their bold Hands ſtrook the damn'd Monſt'r dead</l>
                        <l>Had you a ſpark of ancient Honour left,</l>
                        <l>You ſhould not long be of thy Aid bereft;</l>
                        <l>My Claws are hard and ſharp as e're they were,</l>
                        <l>As fit a Tyrant and his Rats to tear.</l>
                        <l>The Villains that ſupport a Tyrant Crown,</l>
                        <l>This angry Tail will horridly ſweep down;</l>
                        <l>Shake off your Fetters once, and you ſhall ſee,</l>
                        <l>I'll once more ſave you from curſt Slavery.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>She ſaid, and away gallop'd amain,</l>
                        <l>But in hopes they their Senſe would recover again;</l>
                        <l>For a Doctor will never the Fatigue endure.</l>
                        <l>To heal ſuch dull Blockheads, that don't love the Cure.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. III. The <hi>Frogs</hi> Concern.</head>
                     <l>A Generous Race of croaking <hi>Frogs,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which lay entrench't betwixt two Bogs.</l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96878:53"/>
                     <l>Who as the morning Sun did ſhine,</l>
                     <l>Daily encreaſt their ſtock divine;</l>
                     <l>Juſt as the Solar Influence burn'd,</l>
                     <l>Prolifick ſpawn to Life was turn'd,</l>
                     <l>Until the young ones had at length</l>
                     <l>An equal Vigor, equal Strength.</l>
                     <l>So numerous at length they prove,</l>
                     <l>They ſupplicate mighty <hi>Jove;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A King and Governour they crave,</l>
                     <l>As other Beaſts and Inſects have:</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Jove</hi> allow'd all Mortal Elves,</l>
                     <l>To chuſe a Monarch for themſelves.</l>
                     <l>The Croaking Elders now conſult</l>
                     <l>About a King, and the Reſult</l>
                     <l>Was, that a neighb'ring Log ſhould be</l>
                     <l>Executor of Monarchy.</l>
                     <l>About the Log their Heads they raiſe,</l>
                     <l>In ſounds uncouth they croak his Praiſe:</l>
                     <l>At length ſome crawl upon his Top,</l>
                     <l>And frisk about, and croak and hop:</l>
                     <l>Says one <hi>Frog,</hi> Here's fine buſineſs done,</l>
                     <l>Was e're a King thus trampl'd one?</l>
                     <l>'Troth, ſays another antient <hi>Frog,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>We'll ne'r be govern'd by a Log;</l>
                     <l>The heat at length ſo far aroſe,</l>
                     <l>They did the Loggerhead depoſe.</l>
                     <l>To new Election they proceed,</l>
                     <l>And to their Hearts content ſucceed;</l>
                     <l>A neighbouring Stork at length they choſe,</l>
                     <l>Which ſhou'd their Heats and Feuds compoſe:</l>
                     <l>He took upon him the Command</l>
                     <l>Of all the People in <hi>Frogland;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But he as t'other 'fore had done,</l>
                     <l>Made it an Arbitrary Throne;</l>
                     <l>Up from the Mud the <hi>Frogs</hi> would pick,</l>
                     <l>And ſqueeze their Corps within his Beak,</l>
                     <l>One <hi>Frog</hi> much wiſer than the reſt,</l>
                     <l>To theſe about him thus addreſt:</l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96878:53"/>
                     <l>Good Friends, this is confounded work;</l>
                     <l>Shall we be govern'd by a Stork;</l>
                     <l>To have our Bones in pieces torn,</l>
                     <l>Our young ones eat juſt as they'r born?</l>
                     <l>As if Kings only had a Power</l>
                     <l>To ruin Subjects and devour;</l>
                     <l>I think 'tis juſt to chuſe agen:</l>
                     <l>The brood of <hi>Frogs</hi> all croak'd, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The next they choſe was a dull Aſs,</l>
                     <l>Which prov'd as bad as t'other was;</l>
                     <l>For tho' he was not ſo malicious,</l>
                     <l>His folly made him as pernicious;</l>
                     <l>Stumbling on Empire, oft he ſtood</l>
                     <l>Upon his Subjects choak's in Mud:</l>
                     <l>Whole beds of Spawn he did deſtroy,</l>
                     <l>At every flounce did <hi>Frogs</hi> annoy.</l>
                     <l>The Devil's in't, ſaid one, for we</l>
                     <l>In chuſing Kings ſtill wretched be.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thus often we have choſe a King,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſtill have found it the ſame thing.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. IV. The <hi>Kees</hi> and the <hi>Hornet.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Hive of <hi>Bees</hi> had plunder'd ev'ry Field,</l>
                     <l>And ev'ry Herb dees Wax or Hony yield:</l>
                     <l>Large Troops of Winged force they daily arm,</l>
                     <l>Large as the Flocks that about <hi>Hybla</hi> ſwarm;</l>
                     <l>From diſtant Fields did ev'ry Evening come,</l>
                     <l>Loaden with Sweets and wholſom Hony home:</l>
                     <l>Bleſt with abundant Wealth the Sworm do's thrive</l>
                     <l>Beneath the Bleſſings of a well-ſtock't Hive.</l>
                     <l>But Wealth and Luxury together go,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Bees,</hi> when rich, do vain and wanton grow;</l>
                     <l>Pamper'd with Food, they loath their happy Face,</l>
                     <l>And Changlings like, attempt to change their State.</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96878:54"/>
                     <l>Large Herds they ſaw, as they abroad did rove,</l>
                     <l>Govern'd by Monarchs, by the leave of <hi>Jove.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>They <hi>Jupiter</hi> invoke, that alſo he</l>
                     <l>Would pleaſe to favour them with Monarchy.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Jove</hi> from <hi>Olympus</hi> nodding gave conſent,</l>
                     <l>And ſtrait the <hi>Bees</hi> to an Election went.</l>
                     <l>An o'regrown <hi>Hornet</hi> in an Oaken-Tree,</l>
                     <l>Was what they chooſe, and muſt their Sov'raign be:</l>
                     <l>For Bulk and Valour was elected King,</l>
                     <l>The greateſt Warrior ever drew a Sting.</l>
                     <l>His Paunch more Hony ſtill did bear away</l>
                     <l>Then ten ſtrong <hi>Bees</hi> could gather in a Day.</l>
                     <l>But what was worſe, he often wou'd invite</l>
                     <l>His Family to dine and ſup at Night:</l>
                     <l>His num'rous Fav'rites did devour more</l>
                     <l>Than his ſmall Regions ever ſaw before;</l>
                     <l>His lazy Drones did more Proviſion ſpoil,</l>
                     <l>Than is the product of a Summers toil.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Bees</hi> thus robb'd of all their Hony, grieve;</l>
                     <l>'Tis Winter too, they know not how to live.</l>
                     <l>Their Monarch goes to rob another Swarm,</l>
                     <l>And there remain till Summer's heat ſhall warm.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Bees</hi> bereav'd of all their Nouriſhment,</l>
                     <l>Their Wax decay'd, and all their Hony ſpent;</l>
                     <l>Around their Hive their Obſequies they ſing,</l>
                     <l>Lament their Fortune, and they curſe their King.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. V. The <hi>Lion</hi> and <hi>Fox.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Youthful <hi>Lion</hi> in the Wood,</l>
                     <l>Of Bulk and Nature ſtrong;</l>
                     <l>Still us'd to rav'ning and to blood,</l>
                     <l>And came to Empire young:</l>
                     <l>He too, as other Monarchs uſe,</l>
                     <l>New Methods did purſue:</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96878:54"/>
                     <l>His Father's Fav'rites did refuſe;</l>
                     <l>And choſe a ſet of new.</l>
                     <l>He having lov'd, and us'd to gore;</l>
                     <l>An arbitrary ſway,</l>
                     <l>A baſe, a wild Deſpotick Pow'r</l>
                     <l>His Subjects muſt obey.</l>
                     <l>But want of Brains do ſtill attend</l>
                     <l>Unlimited Command:</l>
                     <l>And therefore he would have ſome Friend</l>
                     <l>Might Buſineſs underſtand.</l>
                     <l>There was a cunning <hi>Fox</hi> liv'd near,</l>
                     <l>For many years had kill'd</l>
                     <l>The neighb'ring Lambs and Poultry there,</l>
                     <l>With Bones his Kennel fill'd.</l>
                     <l>He ſummon'd <hi>Reynard</hi> to appear,</l>
                     <l>Next Night, at Council Board.</l>
                     <l>Which <hi>Reynard</hi> did, and when was there,</l>
                     <l>Look'd grave as any Lord.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Lion</hi> told him he muſt be</l>
                     <l>The chief Support of State.</l>
                     <l>At which kind <hi>Reynard</hi> bow'd his Knee,</l>
                     <l>And wiſh'd him better Fate.</l>
                     <l>O, ſays the <hi>Lion,</hi> thou art skill'd</l>
                     <l>In Arbitrary Sway:</l>
                     <l>Thou many Beaſts and Fowls haſt kill'd,</l>
                     <l>To govern know'ſt the way.</l>
                     <l>Ask and I'll give thee any thing,</l>
                     <l>Is in my Pow'r to give:</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt be next unto the King</l>
                     <l>As long as I do live.</l>
                     <l>Quoth <hi>Reynard,</hi> make me then the Prieſt,</l>
                     <l>I'll make all Beaſts your Slaves:</l>
                     <l>The Body You, I Soul at leaſt,</l>
                     <l>Wi'll tyrannize by halves.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thus Fate did Men to thraldom bring,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oppreſt juſt like a Beaſt;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rod, ſpur'd, and whip'd by ſuch a King,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ke ſo lewd a Prieſt.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="fable">
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96878:55"/>
                     <head>FAB. VI. The <hi>Weeſil, Rats</hi> and <hi>Mice.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Mighty <hi>Weeſil</hi> of Renown,</l>
                     <l>Well verſt in things of State,</l>
                     <l>Was choſen King all o're the Town,</l>
                     <l>Of all the <hi>Mice</hi> and <hi>Rats.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His Coronation Day was come,</l>
                     <l>And all the Grandees meet</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Weeſil</hi> in a gaudy Room,</l>
                     <l>And bow beneath his Feet.</l>
                     <l>His Chair of State was Rind of Cheeſe,</l>
                     <l>And o're his Royal Head</l>
                     <l>Some Bacon ſwer'd in goodly guiſe,</l>
                     <l>Like Canopy was ſpread.</l>
                     <l>At length he walks and ſtruts about,</l>
                     <l>Like any Lord or Duke;</l>
                     <l>Sometimes he do's one Subject flout,</l>
                     <l>And ſometimes one rebuke.</l>
                     <l>He calls an aged <hi>Rat</hi> aſide,</l>
                     <l>And ask'd him his advice,</l>
                     <l>Whether a Project mayn't be try'd</l>
                     <l>To eat up all the <hi>Mice.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ay, quoth the <hi>Rat,</hi> your Majeſty</l>
                     <l>May be well ſatisfy'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mice</hi> haters are of Monarchy,</l>
                     <l>And Regal State deride.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Rats</hi> and <hi>Weeſils</hi> now devour</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Mice</hi> in pitious ſort,</l>
                     <l>They dye the Cellers with their Gore,</l>
                     <l>And with their Bones they ſport.</l>
                     <l>At length the <hi>Mice</hi> are all deſtroy'd,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Weeſils</hi> and the <hi>Rats</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Would other Food find out abroad,</l>
                     <l>But that they fear'd the Cats.</l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96878:55"/>
                     <l>The <hi>Weeſils</hi> now together plot,</l>
                     <l>How they the <hi>Rats</hi> may eat;</l>
                     <l>Proviſion muſt be daily got,</l>
                     <l>Kings muſt have ſumptuous Meat.</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Rats</hi> now all do go to pot:</l>
                     <l>Some Bak'd, ſome Boil'd, ſome Roaſted;</l>
                     <l>'Tis hop'd they had not then forgot</l>
                     <l>How they the <hi>Mice</hi> accoſted.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thus ſome Men oft by Tyrant Power.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Their Kindred, Subject Slaves devour,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Do all the Villanies are done</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To prop a beaſtly Tyrant Throne;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tho' others Blood the Tyrant fill'd,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>They muſt at length to's Fury yield;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nought ſtops a Tyrant's Courſe but Decollation,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or elſe a modern Abdication.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VII. <hi>Lubberland.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>A Land there is, as Maps do tell,</l>
                     <l>(Tho' they deſcribe it not right well)</l>
                     <l>Nor near the <hi>Hot</hi> nor <hi>Frigid Zone,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But Latitude of fifty one;</l>
                     <l>In Nature's plenty do's abound,</l>
                     <l>With Fruits and Flocks is amply crown'd:</l>
                     <l>The Natives never are content</l>
                     <l>But with tyrannick Government;</l>
                     <l>They Men reſemble by their Faces,</l>
                     <l>But by their Backs reſemble Aſſes</l>
                     <l>For each is born with a great pack,</l>
                     <l>A warlike Saddle on his Back,</l>
                     <l>Which do's adorn the parts are upper.</l>
                     <l>On neither parts they wear a Crupper.</l>
                     <l>Their Kings, as 'tis decreed by <hi>Jove,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Do always jump down from above.</l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96878:56"/>
                     <l>Arm'd <hi>Cap-a-pee</hi> with Boots and Spurs,</l>
                     <l>Juſt fit to mount ſuch ſervile Curs:</l>
                     <l>With Hunting-Whips they daily maul'em</l>
                     <l>And with long rowl'd Spurs do gall 'em.</l>
                     <l>He only is the great <hi>Bravado,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Has moſt the Regal <hi>Baſtinado.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>They leap and jump, and frisk and skip,</l>
                     <l>And ſing the Praiſes of the Whip:</l>
                     <l>They bear the Laſh without bogging,</l>
                     <l>Extol the Royal Art of flogging.</l>
                     <l>With Blanket-Coat and wooden-Shoes,</l>
                     <l>The Man the Camel ſcarce out does.</l>
                     <l>Whilſt Freemen feed on Dainties fine,</l>
                     <l>Theſe do on Bread and Garlick dine;</l>
                     <l>And if they ſpend a <hi>Sous</hi> in Wine,</l>
                     <l>The Health drank round muſt always be;</l>
                     <l>Their Kings applauded Tyranny;</l>
                     <l>Still let 'em be curs'd Slaves for me.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. VIII. <hi>Hawk</hi> and <hi>Birds.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg n="1">
                        <head>I.</head>
                        <l>A <hi>Hawk,</hi> that of Yore</l>
                        <l>Had long weltred in Gore,</l>
                        <l>And many a <hi>Sparrow</hi> had kill'd;</l>
                        <l>By the <hi>Birds</hi> ſhe was told,</l>
                        <l>Now he was grown old,</l>
                        <l>He his number of Sins had fullfil'd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="2">
                        <head>II.</head>
                        <l>No, ſaid the old <hi>Hawk</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>My Actions to balk</l>
                        <l>If you ſhall but once thus <hi>combino,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96878:56"/>
                        <l>The Gods will avenge,</l>
                        <l>My Cauſe will revenge,</l>
                        <l>I may murder ye <hi>Jure Divino.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="3">
                        <head>III.</head>
                        <l>The Gods, ſaid the <hi>Birds,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>We'll not take their words;</l>
                        <l>If they've 'gin you an Abſolute Power,</l>
                        <l>They've 'gin us a part,</l>
                        <l>Is not worth a Fart,</l>
                        <l>While you have a Right to devour.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg n="4">
                        <head>IV.</head>
                        <l>The <hi>Birds</hi> all agreed,</l>
                        <l>And thus 'twas decreed,</l>
                        <l>That Slaves they no longer would be;</l>
                        <l>They throttl'd their King,</l>
                        <l>Then ſweetly did ſing</l>
                        <l>The Praiſes of free Liberty.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. IX. The <hi>Owl</hi> and the <hi>Mice.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>THE harmleſs <hi>Mice</hi> by Tyranny oppreſt,</l>
                     <l>And by the <hi>Owls</hi> vaſt inſolence diſtreſt,</l>
                     <l>Came to a conſult, where they did debate</l>
                     <l>Of Means to ſave their yet declining State.</l>
                     <l>Up ſtands a <hi>Mouſe</hi> of generous noble Blood,</l>
                     <l>Free from the Fears of the more ſlaviſh Brood;</l>
                     <l>Says he, my Project, Sirs, I hope will take,</l>
                     <l>We'll tie a Bell about the <hi>Owls</hi> damn'd Neck:</l>
                     <l>Thus when the Tyrant's Bell do's ever toll</l>
                     <l>Each <hi>Mouſe</hi> ſecures himſelf within his hole.</l>
                     <l>At which a <hi>Mouſe</hi> for Courage fam'd, aroſe,</l>
                     <l>And did as follows to the reſt propoſe;</l>
                     <l>Brethren, ſays he, this Enterprize is vain,</l>
                     <l>There is no end of this Tyrannick Reign,</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96878:57"/>
                     <l>As long as <hi>Owl,</hi> or any of his kind,</l>
                     <l>Shall here Dominion and an Empire find:</l>
                     <l>You may hang Bells about his Neck, but then</l>
                     <l>He pecks it off, and turns an <hi>Owl</hi> agen.</l>
                     <l>Let's try for once, ſince our Condition's ſo,</l>
                     <l>What bold <hi>Micean</hi> Potentates can do.</l>
                     <l>The only way to guard our Empire well,</l>
                     <l>Is both to rid out ſelves of <hi>Owl</hi> and Bell.</l>
                     <l>Thus we our State and Freedom ſhall repair,</l>
                     <l>And live as our Fore-fathers were.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. X. <hi>Neptune</hi> and the <hi>Fiſhes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>NEptune</hi> the God of the Tempeſtuous Deep,</l>
                     <l>When's Brother <hi>Boreas</hi> huſh't the Storms aſleep;</l>
                     <l>Upon a Rock erected had his Throne,</l>
                     <l>His Chair of State was carv'd out of the Stone;</l>
                     <l>On either hand the lovely <hi>Mermaids</hi> ſate,</l>
                     <l>The glittering Pageants of the Monarch's State;</l>
                     <l>The golden Treſſes which their Heads adorn.</l>
                     <l>Dy'd with the yellow glittering of the Morn.</l>
                     <l>He ſhook his Trident when both far and near</l>
                     <l>His <hi>Guard du Corps</hi> of Tritons ſhook for fear;</l>
                     <l>One he commanded ſtrait to go and tell.</l>
                     <l>All Clans of Fiſh beneath the Surface dwell,</l>
                     <l>That to his Court they preſently repair,</l>
                     <l>Away the <hi>Triton</hi> flounc'd as ſwift as Air,</l>
                     <l>The ſcaly Tribes in endleſs numbers flock</l>
                     <l>And rendevouz before the Royal Rock;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Neptune</hi> in State unto the brink did go,</l>
                     <l>An view'd the num'rous Shoals of Fiſh below:</l>
                     <l>Then pointing to the <hi>Mermaids,</hi> thus he ſaid,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>See there the lovely work the Gods have made,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>By them and Nature deſtin'd for my own,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The juſt Supporters of my vertuous Throne.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96878:57"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Pleaſure is, that every ſort of Fiſh,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For them do every Day provide a Diſh.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The beſt and wholeſom'ſt Fiſh of every ſort,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And bring them every Day unto the Court.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Each Fiſh beneath the Surface downward darts,</l>
                     <l>But glide along with very heavy Hearts;</l>
                     <l>In vain, ſays one, the heav'nly Sun do's burn,</l>
                     <l>Warm the vaſt Deep, and <hi>Spawn</hi> to <hi>Fiſhes</hi> turn:</l>
                     <l>The Gods its ſeem thus <hi>Neptune</hi> has empower'd,</l>
                     <l>And we are born only to be devour'd;</l>
                     <l>Our Off-ſpring ſtill muſt pay their Parents Scores,</l>
                     <l>Made for a Tyrant's Food, and Bawds and's Whores</l>
                     <l>When vaſt laſcivious Paunches ſpend always,</l>
                     <l>More than the num'rous Shoals of <hi>Fiſh</hi> can raiſe.</l>
                     <l>No more, ſaid he, by my conſent, we'll own</l>
                     <l>A Tyrant's Empire, but abjure his Throne;</l>
                     <l>The watry Tribes the Motion did approve,</l>
                     <l>And to his Station every one did move.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="fable">
                     <head>FAB. XI. The <hi>Aſylum.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>THE Princes once did all combine,</l>
                     <l>The Peoples Liberty to mine;</l>
                     <l>Would make 'em right or wrong obey</l>
                     <l>An abſolute Deſpotick Sway:</l>
                     <l>One Method, was to make us poor,</l>
                     <l>By loading Taxes more and more;</l>
                     <l>For when to Poverty Men fall,</l>
                     <l>They eaſily are brought to thrall:</l>
                     <l>And when their Spirit's ſunk and gone,</l>
                     <l>Tyrants may lay vaſt Burthens on.</l>
                     <l>This did in ſome, in all it cou'd</l>
                     <l>Not do: Some Men had better Blood,</l>
                     <l>And tho' they could not mend their Fate</l>
                     <l>They murmur'd at the Tyrant's hate;</l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96878:58"/>
                     <l>Which ſo incenc'd the Tyrant's Ire,</l>
                     <l>Some they condemn'd to rav'nous fire;</l>
                     <l>Some were to ſlaviſh Gallies ſent,</l>
                     <l>Others in Fetters did lament.</l>
                     <l>Some Men were ſtrangl'd in their Beds,</l>
                     <l>Others were hang'd, ſome loſt their Heads;</l>
                     <l>Some whipt till bleeding Backs were kill'd,</l>
                     <l>The Lands with Tyranny were fill'd;</l>
                     <l>But thoſe whom better luck and hap</l>
                     <l>Did favour with a wiſh'd eſcape,</l>
                     <l>A City on <hi>Batavian</hi> Shoar,</l>
                     <l>Did ſhelter from the Ills before;</l>
                     <l>Where native Liberty do's thrive,</l>
                     <l>And no curſt Tyranny can live.</l>
                     <l>Long live great City, Favourite of Heav'n,</l>
                     <l>And never want thoſe Bleſſings thou haſt giv'n.</l>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="half_title">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:58"/>
                  <p>A Dialogue between Bow-Steeple DRAGON, AND THE Exchange GRASHOPER.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="dialogue">
                  <pb facs="tcp:96878:59"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96878:59"/>
                  <head>Eccleſia &amp; Factio. <hi>A DIALOGUE,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dragon.</speaker>
                     <l>TEll me, proud Inſect, ſince thou can'ſt not Fly,</l>
                     <l>By what aſſiſtance thou art Hopp'd ſo high:</l>
                     <l>The buſie ſwarms of Gnats and Waſps around</l>
                     <l>With Hum, and Buz, thy Revelations ſound,</l>
                     <l>And cry in thee (alone) their happineſs is found.</l>
                     <l>Me they Deſpiſe, and thee they Praiſe aloud,</l>
                     <l>Admire thee, and Adore thee as a God:</l>
                     <l>Miſled by falſe Enthuſiaſtick Light,</l>
                     <l>They've rais'd thee now to a Deſtructive hight,</l>
                     <l>Who reſtleſs ſtriv'ſt, by thy accuſtom'd ways,</l>
                     <l>To ſtain thoſe Glories, which thou ne'er could'ſt raiſe;</l>
                     <l>And like your Dam (the <hi>Babylonian</hi> Beaſt)</l>
                     <l>Cry down thoſe Truths (by which Mankind are Bleſt)</l>
                     <l>Which Reaſon, well as Faith, makes manifeſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Graſhoper.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy Scaly Body, and Aſpiring Wings,</l>
                     <l>Thy furious Tallons, and thy frightful Stings,</l>
                     <l>Makes thee ſeem Monſtrous to our milder Flock,</l>
                     <l>Who Dreaded once, but now Diſdains thy Yoke:</l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96878:60"/>
                     <l>You'd bind our Souls, b'Omnipotence made free,</l>
                     <l>And Rob us of that Heav'n-born Liberty,</l>
                     <l>To which we have a Right, as clear as thee</l>
                     <l>My Sons thou wou'dſt unreaſonably confine</l>
                     <l>To worſhip God, within no Walls but thine,</l>
                     <l>As if the Prayers, from other Temples ſent,</l>
                     <l>Of ſighing Souls, who faithfully Repent,</l>
                     <l>Were Scorn'd, and by repulſion backward driven,</l>
                     <l>Vaniſh'd in Air, and reach'd no Ear of Heaven.</l>
                     <l>Where is its Goodneſs? What avails its Grace,</l>
                     <l>If our ſincere Repentance wants acceſs,</l>
                     <l>Thro' Heav'ns reſpect to either Time, or Place?</l>
                     <l>Thoſe meaſures but our own Projections be,</l>
                     <l>Unminded of the Great Eternity,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Love Divine moves round the Sinful Ball,</l>
                     <l>To Bleſs each wretch, who on his Mercies call,</l>
                     <l>Without regard to Place, no matter where,</l>
                     <l>If the Heart's Contrit, and the Mind Sincere.</l>
                     <l>Our Humble Guide the great Example yields,</l>
                     <l>Who Pray'd and Preach'd in Gardens, Mounts, and Fields.</l>
                     <l>Temples but Sacred from their uſe became,</l>
                     <l>Our Piety makes any Houſe the ſame:</l>
                     <l>Where e'er we in th' Almighty's Name repair,</l>
                     <l>Omnipotence hath promis'd to be there.</l>
                     <l>Beſides —</l>
                     <l>Our Prayers (by which all-pity'ng Heav'n we move,</l>
                     <l>To grant us His eſtimable Love,</l>
                     <l>When with true Zeal our Pious Souls are warm'd)</l>
                     <l>Makes the Place Holy, whereſoe'er perform'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dragon.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thou know'ſt I'm founded on a fateleſs Rock,</l>
                        <l>Freed from the danger of an envious ſhock,</l>
                        <l>Scripture's my Baſs, Immovable I ſtand,</l>
                        <l>Guarded by Lawful Pow'r, on ev'ry hand.</l>
                        <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96878:60"/>
                        <l>Eſtabliſh'd by a National Conſent,</l>
                        <l>Preach Faith, and Charity, do Ills prevent;</l>
                        <l>And for the Truths I Teach am made Predominant.</l>
                        <l>Stedfaſt and Pure, from Innovations free,</l>
                        <l>Preſerv'd intire from Mutability;</l>
                        <l>Safe from your Pride, and Envy, Arm'd with Law,</l>
                        <l>To humble ſtiff, Preciſians, who withdraw</l>
                        <l>From my Communion, Conſcious to agree</l>
                        <l>With Heads uncover'd, or a bended Knee,</l>
                        <l>And think a Bow a rank Idolatry.</l>
                        <l>Religion, like a Prince, tho' ne'er ſo Pure,</l>
                        <l>By Pow'r to Puniſh, muſt be made ſecure,</l>
                        <l>Or elſe your Saints, to Reformation given,</l>
                        <l>Would quickly cut Ten Thouſand Paths to Heaven.</l>
                        <l>Could I from Factious Inſolence be free,</l>
                        <l>And live unſtain'd, without an Enemy,</l>
                        <l>(But that, till thou art cruſh'd, can never be)</l>
                        <l>Then Church, and State might happily Unite,</l>
                        <l>To Mankinds Safety, and to Heaven's Delight;</l>
                        <l>But you, by <hi>Pride,</hi> are ſwell'd to ſuch a Rage,</l>
                        <l>(Fed by Vice of a Corrupted Age)</l>
                        <l>That now you ſtrike, with Envy, at my Pow'r,</l>
                        <l>And aim'ſt above my Sacred Head to tow'r:</l>
                        <l>But all in vain—</l>
                        <l>For that Bleſt Edifice can never drop,</l>
                        <l>Which, when aſſail'd, good Heav'n is ſtill the prop.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>You urge a <hi>Barn,</hi> or <hi>Stable,</hi> where you Meet,</l>
                        <l>A <hi>Field,</hi> a <hi>Coffee-Houſe, Dancing-School,</hi> or <hi>Street,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Are fit for Heav'nly Worſhip, and for <hi>Prayer</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Sacred, as unpoluted Temples are</l>
                        <l>Rare Arrogance indeed, ſo vilely prone,</l>
                        <l>To juſtify Irreverence to a God-head done.</l>
                        <l>A Room where Men their common Luſts purſue,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Drink Swear, Lye, Cheat,</hi> all Worldly-buſineſs do,</l>
                        <l>In Chriſtian Reaſon, is a hopeful Place</l>
                        <l>To beg God's Preſence, or exprect His Grace;</l>
                        <l>Whilſt His own Houſe, for Holy uſe ordain'd,</l>
                        <l>To Him Erected, by our Sins unſtain'd,</l>
                        <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96878:61"/>
                        <l>Shall be Deſpis'd, and Unregarded ſtand,</l>
                        <l>A uſeleſs Fabrick, in an Impious Land:</l>
                        <l>Yet do'ſt thou grumble in oppreſſive Tones,</l>
                        <l>And rail at me for Perſecutions.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If you, through ſtudy'd Prejudice, retire</l>
                        <l>From what the Laws of God, and Man require,</l>
                        <l>A Legal Force may juſtly then be us'd;</l>
                        <l>Such Factious Serpents may in time be bruis'd:</l>
                        <l>My <hi>Pow'r</hi>'s from <hi>God,</hi> and in his Word declare,</l>
                        <l>To thoſe who to my Laws bear no regard,</l>
                        <l>Heav'ns <hi>Puniſhments</hi> are juſt, as to the Good Reward</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Scriptures whatſoe'er I Teach contain,</l>
                        <l>What's Eaſie I Recite, and what's Hard Explain:</l>
                        <l>Vertue commend to <hi>Practice,</hi> Sin reprove,</l>
                        <l>Excite to <hi>Faith, Hope, Charity,</hi> and <hi>Love:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Obedience, Loyalty, Repentance, Prayer,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The uſe of what we Spend, or what we Spare.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Truth</hi> I advance, and what is Falſe ſuppreſs,</l>
                        <l>You can no more than theſe I do no leſs.</l>
                        <l>Then tell me what ſtrange Fever in the Head,</l>
                        <l>At firſt thoſe Superſtitious Frenzys bred?</l>
                        <l>From whence you raiſe the cauſeleſs Diſcontent,</l>
                        <l>Which makes you from my Temples thus Diſſent?</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Graſhoper.</speaker>
                     <l>Superfluous Rites there are, which you maintain,</l>
                     <l>And hold as Decencies, which I think Vain.</l>
                     <l>Look back upon your boaſted Pedigree,</l>
                     <l>One part deriv'd of <hi>Rome</hi>'s Idolatry,</l>
                     <l>From whoſe fantaſtick Cuſtoms you have drawn,</l>
                     <l>Square Caps, low Bows, your Surpliſs, and your Lawn.</l>
                     <l>Proud Lazy <hi>Prelates;</hi> with Pluralities,</l>
                     <l>Who ſpeak but by their hair-brain'd Deputies,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Junior Years no Truths obſcure can reach;</l>
                     <l>And ſeldom are ſo Wiſe,, as thoſe they Teach.</l>
                     <l>Your Maſs-like Service, with your noiſie Toots,</l>
                     <l>Of hum drum Organs, Fiddle Faddles and Flutes,</l>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96878:61"/>
                     <l>Your high flown Doctrines to advance a State</l>
                     <l>And pleaſe it, till Unlawfully made Great,</l>
                     <l>Then turn your Holy Flat'ries to its Fate.</l>
                     <l>Theſe I diſlike, from theſe (in chief) Diſſent,</l>
                     <l>As quite repugnant to the Lord's intent.</l>
                     <l>Theſe are the ſumptuous Trappings of the Whore,</l>
                     <l>The Marks and Patches which ſhe always wore.</l>
                     <l>Theſe are her ſtudy'd, and prevailing Charms,</l>
                     <l>Which but the loſer part of Fancy warms,</l>
                     <l>And draws unwary Youth to her Adult'rous Arms.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dragon.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>External Order firſt informs our Sence,</l>
                        <l>And raiſes in us a due Reverence,</l>
                        <l>Either towards <hi>Place,</hi> or <hi>Perſon,</hi> where we ſee</l>
                        <l>Concurrent parts, in Noble Form, agree,</l>
                        <l>And tend to a peculiar Harmony.</l>
                        <l>Or why did the Creator ſhape the World</l>
                        <l>From a dark Maſs, together rudely hurl'd?</l>
                        <l>But that in ev'y part, Mankind ſhould ſee,</l>
                        <l>The ſtrokes of an All-pow'rful Deity.</l>
                        <l>From whence the light of Faith does firſt ariſe,</l>
                        <l>And makes our Reaſon ſubject to our Eyes,</l>
                        <l>For ev'ry wond'rous work of Heav'n we ſee,</l>
                        <l>Gives freſh Aſſurance of Eternity;</l>
                        <l>And by it's Graceful Order ſtrikes an Awe,</l>
                        <l>Humbles our Souls, and does Obedience draw,</l>
                        <l>By Natural means, to Heav'n, and Nature's Law:</l>
                        <l>Therefore, ſuch decent Rites do I diſpence,</l>
                        <l>As beſt ſhall Humble, and Affect the Senſe;</l>
                        <l>And in my Sons beget a Graceful Reverence.</l>
                        <l>How Inſolent it looks? How Evil bred,</l>
                        <l>T' approach God's Preſence with a cover'd Head;</l>
                        <l>Yet to a Great-man Couch, with Hat in Hand,</l>
                        <l>And bare, before the Wealthy Idol, ſtand.</l>
                        <l>Or at Devotion ſo neglectful be,</l>
                        <l>As quite abandon all Humility;</l>
                        <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96878:62"/>
                        <l>And rather than to bended Knees ſubmit,</l>
                        <l>In diſreſpectful Poſtures, Lolling ſit.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Next, with Church Government you diſagree,</l>
                        <l>And cauſleſly condemn our Hierarchy:</l>
                        <l>Rail at my Biſhops, angry at their State,</l>
                        <l>And Envy them; whoſe Merit made them Great;</l>
                        <l>The Learn'd and Pious Characters they wear,</l>
                        <l>Hath rais'd them to the Dignities they bear.</l>
                        <l>Unſtain'd their Lives, they are as Guardians choſe,</l>
                        <l>To ſave the Church from Errour, and from Foes:</l>
                        <l>Without whoſe Conduct, and Authority,</l>
                        <l>Religions Priſtine ſtate can never be</l>
                        <l>Kept from Erroneous Innovations free,</l>
                        <l>But ſtand expos'd to every abuſe.</l>
                        <l>That each Fanatick whimſie ſhall produce.</l>
                        <l>Then ſure ſuch Men, who by a painful Life,</l>
                        <l>(Thro' Grace) to Knowledge more ſublim'd arrive;</l>
                        <l>And with the piercing Eyes of Reaſon, ſee</l>
                        <l>Thro' all the Miſteries of Divinity,</l>
                        <l>Juſtly deſerve a Spiritual advance,</l>
                        <l>Above an unlearn'd or a half-learn'd Dunce;</l>
                        <l>Whoſe rowling Eyes, feign'd Looks, and yawning Jaws,</l>
                        <l>Can nothing utter, but with Hums, and Haughs;</l>
                        <l>Inſpir'd with Ignorance, than roars aloud</l>
                        <l>Audacious Nonſenſe, to a Brainleſs Croud</l>
                        <l>'Tis theſe, who from their Cradle are miſled,</l>
                        <l>And backward taught, to Factious Pulpits bred,</l>
                        <l>Who, with impetious vi'lence, headlong run,</l>
                        <l>Purſuing Ills, their Rebel Sires begun.</l>
                        <l>Thus in their Frahers Faults they perſevere,</l>
                        <l>And, by Inſtinct of Nature, envious Dunces are;</l>
                        <l>Theſe, thro' their barren Ignorance, exclaim</l>
                        <l>Againſt all Order, and the Church defame.</l>
                        <l>Pelting with Factious, and Calumnious Lyes,</l>
                        <l>That Sacred Power to which they cannot riſe:</l>
                        <l>Spurning at all Eccleſiaſtick Pomp,</l>
                        <l>True Zealous Sons of the deteſted Rump,</l>
                        <l>Waiting the lucky Minute to be turn'd up Trump.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96878:62"/>
                     <speaker>Graſhoper.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe bad Aſperſions from afar you fetch,</l>
                     <l>Serve, but as Bullets, to enlarge the Breach.</l>
                     <l>Why ſo Diſturb'd, ſo Scornful, and ſo High?</l>
                     <l>You re but a Weather cock as well as I.</l>
                     <l>Boaſt of fix'd Fundamenrals, yet I find.</l>
                     <l>For Intereſt, you can Turn with ev'ry Wind.</l>
                     <l>Where's Right Divine, your Paſſive, and your Non,</l>
                     <l>The Bubble's once blown up, now, poh, they're gone,</l>
                     <l>Where is your Loyalty, ſo ſubt'ly ſhown,</l>
                     <l>Sometimes to th' Prince and ſometimes to the Throne,</l>
                     <l>Sometimes to both, ſometimes to ne'er a one,</l>
                     <l>Thus is it Logically plac'd behind</l>
                     <l>So many School boys Querks, 'tis hard to find,</l>
                     <l>When the great Change (by Heav'ns permition try'd)</l>
                     <l>Your Churches Doctrine, and her Clergies Pride.</l>
                     <l>Some Conſcientious Fools, 'tis true, turn'd out,</l>
                     <l>But all the Wiſer Shepherds fac'd about;</l>
                     <l>And, like good Men, could blacken and upbraid</l>
                     <l>That ſinking Pow'r, for which before they Pray'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dragon.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Scandal (as you are wont) I know you chuſe,</l>
                        <l>As the beſt Weapon, of Offence to uſe,</l>
                        <l>Whether, on ſearch, it True, or Falſe be found,</l>
                        <l>No matter which, if you can make it wound.</l>
                        <l>But know my Armour's temper'd againſt Fate;</l>
                        <l>And much to hard, for you to penetrate:</l>
                        <l>The Iron Walls, my treaſur'd Truths defend,</l>
                        <l>Reverb'rate all the poiſonous Balls you ſend.</l>
                        <l>You charge me with the want of Loyalty,</l>
                        <l>That am the chief ſupport of Monarchy:</l>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96878:63"/>
                        <l>By my High Prieſt the Holy Oyl's apply'd</l>
                        <l>By me Kings Reign, are Crown'd, and Sanctifi'd;</l>
                        <l>I am on Earth their Safety a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> to Heav'n their Guide.</l>
                        <l>By me the Factious Falſhoods are ſuppreſt,</l>
                        <l>Scatter'd by reſtleſs Rebels, to moleſt.</l>
                        <l>The happy quiet of a Peaceful Reign,</l>
                        <l>Which Traitors Envy, and blind Fools Diſdain.</l>
                        <l>Duty to Kings I to the Publick teach,</l>
                        <l>To Loyalty Excite, Perſwade, Beſeech,</l>
                        <l>That all things to the Throne be eaſie made,</l>
                        <l>And him thereon be Rev'renc'd, and Obey'd.</l>
                        <l>What are all theſe, but Marks of Loyalty,</l>
                        <l>Religious Graces, manifeſt in me,</l>
                        <l>Vertues, I find, too bright for thy dull Eyes to ſee.</l>
                        <l>But pray your Reaſons to the World impart,</l>
                        <l>Why now you from your old Opinion ſtart.</l>
                        <l>In happy days, when <hi>Charles</hi> the Scepter ſway'd,</l>
                        <l>When baſe Deſigns, by you know who, were laid,</l>
                        <l>Then all your Awkard, Canting Brood profeſt</l>
                        <l>'Twas Damnable, the Bread of Life to Taſte,</l>
                        <l>Within my Sacred Temple-Walls, but now,</l>
                        <l>What then you held ſo Dang'rous, you Allow.</l>
                        <l>If Once 'twas an Offence ſo great, we know</l>
                        <l>(As you maintain'd, full Twenty Years ago)</l>
                        <l>'Tis now the ſame, and Ever will be ſo.</l>
                        <l>Why do the Grandees of your Leering Tribe,</l>
                        <l>(Who from rank Dugs their prejudice imbibe)</l>
                        <l>So curb their Malice, as conform of late,</l>
                        <l>And with my Flocks they Envy, Congregate.</l>
                        <l>Oft on a Sabbath's Morning have I ſeen</l>
                        <l>Rich Awful Zealots of a bulkey Mein,</l>
                        <l>Cheat Heaven, and diſſemble with the State,</l>
                        <l>To be by Flatt'ry, and Deceit made Great;</l>
                        <l>Viſit my Temples, ſeem devout as Saints;</l>
                        <l>And for their Intereſt, turn baſe Sycophants;</l>
                        <l>Thus with my Worſhip, thro' deſign, agree,</l>
                        <l>And only Mimick, what they hate to be,</l>
                        <l>To climb unfairly to Authority.</l>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96878:63"/>
                        <l>Then, by their own Corrupted Whimſies led,</l>
                        <l>Where the Frape meet, and common Ills are bred;</l>
                        <l>There hear the Church, from whence they came Lampoon'd.</l>
                        <l>And true Religion, by an Ape Buffoon'd;</l>
                        <l>Who o'er his Cuſhion, full of Yawn, and Hum,</l>
                        <l>Stands Gaping like the Bear that beats the Drum.</l>
                        <l>Thus is the After-noon at Meeting ſpent,</l>
                        <l>The Morning in the Church, at Sacrament:</l>
                        <l>Rare pious Chriſtians, full of Faith and Grace,</l>
                        <l>To thus with Heaven, diſſemble for a Place;</l>
                        <l>And pawn their Souls to purchaſe Sword or Mace.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If I am Right, and from Miſtakes moſt free,</l>
                        <l>Why do they not Conform intire to me;</l>
                        <l>If your dark Syſtem, they believe moſt true,</l>
                        <l>Why not alone Communicate with you?</l>
                        <l>Thoſe who for Intereſt, carry fair with both,</l>
                        <l>Are juſt to neither, by their Faith and Troth:</l>
                        <l>But plung'd between two Crimes, to Greatneſs bent,</l>
                        <l>Err with the Wrong, and from the Right Diſſent.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Graſhoper.</speaker>
                     <l>If you make Laws to eclipſe my purer light.</l>
                     <l>And rob my Sons, of what's their native Right,</l>
                     <l>The fault's not theirs, 'tis you incur the blame,</l>
                     <l>The Cunning's on their ſide, on yours the ſhame.</l>
                     <l>Why not by Birth, and Chriſtian Knowledge free</l>
                     <l>To Riches, Honour, and Authority?</l>
                     <l>Why muſt theſe Worldly Comforts reſt in you;</l>
                     <l>Or your Sons count all Pow'r and Place their due?</l>
                     <l>Why may not mine as well aſſiſt the State,</l>
                     <l>And in as great Attempts prove fortunate?</l>
                     <l>If you ſuch Laws procure ſuch Power poſſeſs,</l>
                     <l>As prove a hindrance to our happineſs,</l>
                     <l>How can you juſtly blame us to evade,</l>
                     <l>And leap o'er all the Stumbling-blocks you've laid?</l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96878:64"/>
                     <l>If you ſuch bats to our Preferments make,</l>
                     <l>As Oaths, and Sacraments, for your own Int'reſt ſake,</l>
                     <l>It is no crime in us, the ſame to break or take.</l>
                     <l>If you, attempt, thro' Pride, to keep us low,</l>
                     <l>And we thro' Cunning, your deſigns o'erthrow</l>
                     <l>Call it not Cozening Heaven, but out-witting you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dragon.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>No Laws can ſuch looſe Principles reſtrain,</l>
                        <l>No force can bind you, but a Golden Chain.</l>
                        <l>Int'reſt I find is the prevailing tye,</l>
                        <l>Makes you Approve, Conform, Diſſent, Deny,</l>
                        <l>Oppoſe the Right, or the Wrong Juſtifie.</l>
                        <l>Int'reſt, from me firſt made you Separate,</l>
                        <l>And become Rival to the Church and State</l>
                        <l>Intereſt diſpos'd you to Inteſtine Jars,</l>
                        <l>Improv'd to Bloody, and Domeſtick Wars;</l>
                        <l>Wherein being flatter'd with unjuſt ſucceſs,</l>
                        <l>Trampl'd on Merit, ſpit in Vertues Face;</l>
                        <l>Riffled the Throne, and ſtain'd the Judgment ſeat.</l>
                        <l>With Crimes too black, and dreadful to repeat;</l>
                        <l>As if to you, Omnipotence had given,</l>
                        <l>A Sanguine not a Milky way to Heaven.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Still are your Thoughts by a wild Ambition toſt,</l>
                        <l>Aiming to gain that Pow'r, you juſtly loſt:</l>
                        <l>At all Elections, buſie are your Brood,</l>
                        <l>Heaving and ſhoving 'gainſt the Publick Good.</l>
                        <l>On all Promotions, Zealouſly intent,</l>
                        <l>Squeeſe, Bawl, and Joſtle, till their Breaths are ſpent;</l>
                        <l>Kick, Cuff, and Scandal (heedleſs of the Laws)</l>
                        <l>Tongues, Feet, and Arms, all working for the Cauſe;</l>
                        <l>To raiſe ſome Meager Darlings of their own,</l>
                        <l>Faction in whoſe penurious looks is ſhown:</l>
                        <l>Rich by meer Chance, or Fraud, not Great by merit grown.</l>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96878:64"/>
                        <l>Who can Lye, Cant, Diſſemble, or Forſwear,</l>
                        <l>Declaim againſt, or hear the Common-Prayer;</l>
                        <l>Thro' all Opinions halt, to Lamely reach the Chair.</l>
                        <l>Who can his Conſcience, to his Intereſt mould,</l>
                        <l>Run with the Court, or with the City hold.</l>
                        <l>And without ſhame, can true Reflections Face,</l>
                        <l>Or bear all Scandal, with a comely Grace.</l>
                        <l>And will his Pow'r beyond juſt bounds extend,</l>
                        <l>To injure Foes, or to advance a Friend;</l>
                        <l>Or any thing will do to ſerve a Factious End.</l>
                        <l>Theſe are the worthy <hi>Dolts,</hi> your Sons advance,</l>
                        <l>By their falſe Poles, and double Diligence.</l>
                        <l>Theſe are the Men of merit, they provide,</l>
                        <l>To Row, and Toe, againſt the Wind and Tide;</l>
                        <l>Who in Tempeſtious Diſcords, they create,</l>
                        <l>Sail quite repugnant to the Church and State:</l>
                        <l>Yet to ſuch outward Godlineſs ſeem bent,</l>
                        <l>To Church they'll come, tho' in their Hearts Diſſent</l>
                        <l>But for no Faith, will either Hang or Starve,</l>
                        <l>Both God and Mammon, for advancement ſerve;</l>
                        <l>Thus ſeaſonably comply, or in fit times can ſwerve.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If ſuch unſteddy Rovers bear Command,</l>
                        <l>Whilſt Men of worth, ſhall unregarded ſtand,</l>
                        <l>By Law, and Nature Qualifi'd for Truſt,</l>
                        <l>To ſomething fix'd, and known in all things Juſt.</l>
                        <l>If Men like theſe, ſhall be by Fraud put by,</l>
                        <l>And yield their Rights to the Pedantick Fry;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>England</hi> muſt ſoon from all her Greatneſs fall,</l>
                        <l>And mourn her Antient Glories Funeral.</l>
                        <l>Which Heaven prevent—</l>
                        <l>And (that ſhe may once more her Grandure boaſt)</l>
                        <l>Retrieve her Vertues, now ſo nearly loſt;</l>
                        <l>And from all Factious Quarrels, and Deſpights,</l>
                        <l>Preſerve the <hi>King, Church, Nation,</hi> and our <hi>Rights:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>That in one Faith, we may United be,</l>
                        <l>And accord ſweetly, in juſt Harmony.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
